

Version 2 
For the purposes of screen readers, any mention in this document of Cambridge IGCSE refers to Cambridge International General Certificate of Secondary Education. 

Why choose Cambridge International? 
Cambridge International prepares school students for life, helping them develop an informed curiosity and a lasting passion for learning. We are part of the University of Cambridge. 
Our Cambridge Pathway gives students a clear path for educational success from age 5 to 19. Schools can shape the curriculum around how they want students to learn – with a wide range of subjects and flexible ways to offer them. It helps students discover new abilities and a wider world, and gives them the skills they need for life, so they can achieve at school, university and work. 
Our programmes and qualifications set the global standard for international education. They are created by subject experts, are rooted in academic rigour and reflect the latest educational research. They provide a strong platform for learners to progress from one stage to the next, and are well supported by teaching and learning resources. Learn more about our research at www.cambridgeassessment.org.uk/our-research/ 
We believe education works best when curriculum, teaching, learning and assessment are closely aligned. Our programmes develop deep knowledge, conceptual understanding and higher-order thinking skills, to prepare students for their future. Together with schools, we develop Cambridge learners who are confident, responsible, reflective, innovative and engaged – equipped for success in the modern world. 
Every year, nearly a million Cambridge students from 10000 schools in 160 countries prepare for their future with the Cambridge Pathway. 
School feedback: ‘We think the Cambridge curriculum is superb preparation for university.’ Feedback from: Christoph Guttentag, Dean of Undergraduate Admissions, Duke University, USA 
Quality management 

Cambridge International is committed to providing exceptional quality. In line with this commitment, our quality management system for the provision of international education programmes and qualifications for students aged 5 to 19 is independently certified as meeting the internationally recognised standard, ISO 9001:2015. Learn more at www.cambridgeinternational.org/about-us/our-standards/ 
©Cambridge University Press & Assessment September 2023 
Cambridge Assessment International Education is part of Cambridge University Press & Assessment. Cambridge University Press & Assessment is a department of the University of Cambridge. Cambridge University Press & Assessment retains the copyright on all its publications. Registered centres are permitted to copy 
material from this booklet for their own internal use. However, we cannot give permission to centres to photocopy any material that is acknowledged to a third party even for internal use within a centre. 

Contents 
Why choose Cambridge International? ........................................................................ 2 
1 Why choose this syllabus? ........................................................................................ 4 
2 Syllabus overview ....................................................................................................... 7 
Aims 7 Content overview 8 Assessment overview 9 Assessment objectives 10 
3 Subject content .........................................................................................................11 
4 Details of the assessment ....................................................................................... 37 
Paper 1 – Theory 37 Paper 2 – Document Production, Databases and Presentations 37 Paper 3 – Spreadsheets and Website Authoring 38 Command words 39 
5 What else you need to know ................................................................................... 40 
Before you start 40 Making entries 41 Accessibility and equality 41 After the exam 42 How students and teachers can use the grades 43 Changes to this syllabus for 2026, 2027 and 2028 44 
Important: Changes to this syllabus 


The latest syllabus is version 1, published September 2026. There are no significant changes which affect 
teaching. Any textbooks endorsed to support the syllabus for examination from 2023 are still suitable for use with this syllabus. 
1 Why choose this syllabus? 
Key benefits 
Cambridge IGCSE is the world’s most popular international qualification for 14 to 16 year olds, although it can be taken by students of other ages. It is tried, tested and trusted. 
Students can choose from 70 subjects in any combination – it is taught by over 5000 schools in 150 countries. 
Our programmes promote a thorough knowledge and understanding of a subject and help to develop the skills learners need for their next steps in education or employment. 
Cambridge IGCSE Information and Communication Technology provides learners with the ability to use a broad range of ICT skills and encourages knowledge and understanding of the development of ICT systems, networks and their safe use. 
This course provides learners with the ability to understand the rapid change of ICT in a technology-based world and the impact ICT has on the world.  
Learners in a modern ICT based world need to have the ability to gather, process and manipulate data; this course helps learners to fulfil this. 
Our approach in Cambridge IGCSE Information and Communication Technology encourages learners to be: 
confident, in applying knowledge and understanding of ICT technologies and using skills to solve ICT problems, both as individuals and working with others 
responsible, for themselves, responsive to and respectful of others with particular consideration to physical safety and eSafety 
reflective, in their ability to learn and develop ICT skills 
innovative, in the way that they use ICT-based solutions to solve problems and identify alternative solutions to solve problems 
engaged, socially, in the work that they undertake and to interrogate unfamiliar situations to provide ICT-based solutions. 


School feedback: ‘The strength of Cambridge IGCSE qualifications is internationally recognised and has provided an international pathway for our students to continue their studies around the world.’ 
Feedback from: Gary Tan, Head of Schools and CEO, Raffles Group of Schools, Indonesia 
Back to contents page 

International recognition and acceptance 
Our expertise in curriculum, teaching and learning, and assessment is the basis for the recognition of our programmes and qualifications around the world. The combination of knowledge and skills in Cambridge IGCSE Information and Communication Technology gives learners a solid foundation for further study. Candidates who achieve grades A* to C are well prepared to follow a wide range of courses including Cambridge International AS & A Level Information Technology. 
Cambridge IGCSEs are accepted and valued by leading universities and employers around the world as evidence of academic achievement. Cambridge students can be confident that their qualifications will be understood and valued throughout their education and career, in their home country and internationally. Many universities require a combination of Cambridge International AS & A Levels and Cambridge IGCSEs or equivalent to meet their entry requirements. 
UK ENIC, the national agency in the UK for the recognition and comparison of international qualifications and skills, has carried out an independent benchmarking study of Cambridge IGCSE and found it to be comparable to the standard of the GCSE in the UK. This means students can be confident that their Cambridge IGCSE qualifications are accepted as equivalent to UK GCSEs by leading universities worldwide. 
Learn more at www.cambridgeinternational.org/recognition 
School feedback: ‘Cambridge IGCSE is one of the most sought-after and recognised qualifications in the world. It is very popular in Egypt because it provides the perfect preparation for success at advanced level programmes.’ 
Feedback from: Managing Director of British School of Egypt BSE 
Back to contents page 

Supporting teachers 
We believe education is most effective when curriculum, teaching and learning, and assessment are closely aligned. We provide a wide range of resources, detailed guidance, innovative training and targeted professional development so that you can give your students the best possible preparation for Cambridge IGCSE. To find out which resources are available for each syllabus go to our School Support Hub. 
The School Support Hub is our secure online site for Cambridge teachers where you can find the resources you need to deliver our programmes. You can also keep up to date with your subject and the global Cambridge community through our online discussion forums. 
Find out more at www.cambridgeinternational.org/support 
Support for Cambridge IGCSE  
Planning and preparation • Syllabuses • Schemes of work • Specimen Question Papers and Mark Schemes • Teacher guides • Next step guides  Teaching and assessment • Endorsed resources • Online forums  Learning and revision • Example candidate responses • Past papers and mark schemes • Learner guides  Results • Candidate Results Service • Principal examiner reports for teachers • Results Analysis  

Sign up for email notifications about changes to syllabuses, including new and revised products and services, at www.cambridgeinternational.org/syllabusupdates 
Syllabuses and specimen materials represent the final authority on the content and structure of all of our assessments. 
Professional development 
Find the next step on your professional development journey. 
• 
Introductory Professional Development – An introduction to Cambridge programmes and qualifications. 

• 
Extension Professional Development – Develop your understanding of Cambridge programmes and qualifications to build confidence in your delivery. 

• 
Enrichment Professional Development – Transform your approach to teaching with our Enrichment workshops. 

• 
Cambridge Professional Development Qualifications (PDQs) – Practice-based programmes that transform professional learning for practising teachers. Available at Certificate and Diploma level. 


Find out more at: 
www.cambridgeinternational.org/support-and-training-for-schools/professional-development/ 

Supporting exams officers 

We provide comprehensive support and guidance for all Cambridge exams officers. Find out more at: www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide 
Back to contents page 



2 Syllabus overview 
Aims 
The aims describe the purposes of a course based on this syllabus. 
The aims are to enable students to develop: 
• 
an understanding of the basic components, use and application of different ICT systems and networks 

• 
the skills to analyse, design, implement, test and evaluate ICT systems 

• 
the skills to understand the impact of current and new technologies on methods of working in the outside world 

• 
the ability to recognise potential risks when using ICT, and use safe, secure and responsible practice. 




Cambridge Assessment International Education is an education organisation and politically neutral. The contents of this syllabus, examination papers and associated materials do not endorse any political view. We endeavour to treat all aspects of the exam process neutrally. 
Back to contents page 

Content overview 
1 
Types and components of computer systems 2 
Input and output devices 3 Storage devices and media 4 
Networks and the effects of using them 5 
The effects of using IT 6 ICT applications 7 The systems life cycle 8 Safety and security 9 Audience 10 Communication 11 File management 12 Images 13 Layout 14 Styles 15 Proofing 16 Graphs and charts 17 Document production 18 Databases 19 Presentations 20 Spreadsheets 21 Website authoring 
Back to contents page 

Assessment overview 
All candidates take three components. Candidates will be eligible for grades A* to G. 
All candidates take: and: 
Paper 1 1 hour 30 minutes Paper 2 2 hours 15 minutes Theory 40% Document Production, Databases 30% and Presentations 
80 marks 70 marks 
Questions will be based on sections 1–21 of the subject content This test assesses the practical skills needed to use the applications covered in sections 17, 18 
All questions are compulsory and 19 of the subject content Externally assessed 
Candidates must demonstrate the practical skills relevant to sections 11–16 All tasks are compulsory Externally assessed 
and: 
Component 3 2 hours 15 minutes Spreadsheets and Website Authoring 30% 
70 marks This test assesses the practical skills needed to use the applications covered in sections 20 and 21 of the subject content 
Candidates must demonstrate the practical skills relevant to sections 11–16 All tasks are compulsory Externally assessed 

Information on availability is in the Before you start section. 
Check the timetable at www.cambridgeinternational.org/timetables for the test date window for Components 2 and 3. 
Back to contents page 

Assessment objectives 
The assessment objectives (AOs) are: 
AO1 Recall, select and communicate knowledge and understanding of ICT AO2 Apply knowledge, understanding and skills to produce ICT-based solutions AO3 Analyse, evaluate, make reasoned judgements and present conclusions 
Weighting for assessment objectives 
The approximate weightings allocated to each of the assessment objectives (AOs) are summarised below. 
Assessment objectives as a percentage of the qualification 
Assessment objective Weighting in IGCSE % 
AO1 Recall, select and communicate knowledge and understanding of ICT 32 
AO2 Apply knowledge, understanding and skills to produce ICT-based solutions 60 
AO3 Analyse, evaluate, make reasoned judgements and present conclusions 8 
Total 100 
Assessment objectives as a percentage of each component  
Assessment objective  Weighting in components %  
Paper 1  Paper 2  Paper 3  

AO1 Recall, select and communicate knowledge and 80 0 0 understanding of ICT 
AO2 Apply knowledge, understanding and skills to produce 0 100 100 ICT-based solutions 
AO3 Analyse, evaluate, make reasoned judgements and present 20 0 0 conclusions 
Total 100 100 100 
Back to contents page 



3 Subject content 
This syllabus gives you the flexibility to design a course that will interest, challenge and engage your learners. Where appropriate you are responsible for selecting resources and examples to support your learners’ study. These should be appropriate for the learners’ age, cultural background and learning context as well as complying with your school policies and local legal requirements. 
The following information identifies content which must be covered within all topics. Where the term ‘including’ is used, everything listed must be studied. However, this list is not exhaustive and other related aspects should also be studied. 
Note that no marks are awarded for brand names of software packages or hardware in candidate responses. 
1 Types and components of computer systems 
1.1 Hardware and software  
Candidates should know and understand:  Notes and Guidance  
Hardware  Hardware consists of the physical components of a  
computer system  
Internal components including Central Processing  
Unit (CPU), processor, motherboard  
Internal memory including random access memory  
(RAM), read-only memory (ROM)  
Hardware components including graphics card,  
sound card, Network Interface Card (NIC), camera,  
internal/external storage devices, input and output  
devices  

Software Software are programs for controlling the operation 
of a computer or processing of electronic data Applications software provides the services that the user requires to solve a task 
Examples of applications software including word processing, spreadsheet, database management systems, control, measurement, applets and apps, video editing, graphics editing, audio editing, computer aided design (CAD) 
System software provides the services that the 
computer requires to operate Examples of system software including compilers, linkers, device drivers, operating systems and utilities 

Analogue and digital data Characteristics of analogue and digital data Differences between analogue and digital data The need to convert: 
• 
analogue to digital data so it can be processed by a computer 

• 
digital data to analogue data so it can be used to control devices 



Back to contents page 
1.2 The main components of computer systems  
Candidates should know and understand:  Notes and Guidance  
Central Processing Unit (CPU)  The role of the CPU in processing instructions  
entered into the computer in order to produce an  
output  
Internal memory  Characteristics of ROM and RAM  
Differences between ROM and RAM  
Input and output devices  Characteristics of input and output devices  
Differences between input and output devices  
Backing storage  Characteristics of backing storage  
Differences between backing storage and internal  
memory  
1.3 Operating systems  
Candidates should know and understand:  Notes and Guidance  
Operating systems  Characteristics of operating systems including:  
Command Line Interface (CLI), Graphical User  
Interface (GUI), dialogue based and gesture based  
interface  
Differences between types of operating systems  
Advantages and disadvantages of the different  
types of operating systems  
1.4 Types of computer  
Candidates should know and understand:  Notes and Guidance  
Desktop computer  Characteristics of a desktop computer  
Uses of a desktop computer including office and  
business management, education, gaming and  
entertainment  
Mobile computers  Characteristics of mobile computers including  
laptop computers, smartphones, tablet and phablet  
computers  
Uses of mobile computers including office and  
business management, education, gaming,  
entertainment and remotely controlled devices  
Advantages and disadvantages of the different  
types of computer including portability and  
expandability  

Back to contents page 
1.5 Emerging technologies 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Impact of emerging technologies 


2 Input and output devices 
2.1 Input devices and their uses 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Input devices 

2.2 Direct data entry and associated devices 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Direct data entry 


2.3 Output devices and their uses 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Output devices 
Notes and Guidance 
Impact on everyday life including Artificial Intelligence (AI), extended reality (virtual and augmented) 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses, advantages and disadvantages of input devices including: keyboard, numeric keypad, pointing devices, remote control, joystick/driving wheel, touch screen (as an input device), scanners,  camera, microphone, sensors, light pen 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses, advantages and disadvantages of direct data entry devices including: magnetic stripe reader, chip and PIN reader, Radio Frequency Identification (RFID) reader, Optical Mark Recognition/Reader (OMR), Optical Character Recognition/Reader (OCR), bar code reader, QR scanner 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses, advantages and disadvantages of output devices including: monitors, touch screen (as an output device), multimedia projector, laser printer, inkjet printer, dot matrix printer, plotter, 3D printers, speaker, actuator 

Back to contents page 
3 



Storage devices and media 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Storage devices 
Storage media 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses, media, advantages and disadvantages of storage devices including magnetic, optical and solid-state 
Magnetic drives including fixed and portable magnetic hard drives, magnetic tape drives 
Optical drives including CD, DVD, Blu-ray Fixed and portable solid-state drive (SSD) including SSD, pen drive, flash drive 
Characteristics, uses, advantages and disadvantages of storage media including magnetic, optical and solid-state 
Magnetic drives including magnetic hard disks, magnetic tape 
Optical discs including CD, DVD, Blu-ray Solid-state media including memory cards (SD, xD, CFast) 

4 Networks and the effects of using them 
4.1 Networks 

Candidates should know and understand: Notes and Guidance 
Router The operation and purpose of a router including: 
• 
connecting networks and devices to the internet 

• 
storing computer addresses in a router 

• 
routing data packets 



Common network devices Including: network interface cards (NIC), hubs, bridges, switches 
wi-fi and Bluetooth The uses of wi-fi and Bluetooth Connecting a device to a network using: 
• 
wi-fi 

• 
Bluetooth 


Similarities and differences between Bluetooth and wi-fi 

Cloud computing The characteristics, uses and issues relating to 
cloud computing How data is stored, managed and shared using cloud computing 
Advantages and disadvantages of using cloud storage compared to other methods 

Back to contents page 
4.1 Networks continued  
Candidates should know and understand:  Notes and Guidance  
Common network environments  Characteristics, uses and purpose of an extranet,  
intranet and the internet  
The differences and similarities between an  
extranet, intranet and the internet  
Network types  Local Area Network (LAN), Wireless Local Area  
Network (WLAN), Wide Area Network (WAN) and  
the differences between these networks  
4.2 Network issues and communication  
Candidates should know and understand:  Notes and Guidance  
Security issues regarding data transfer  Privacy and confidentiality of data transfer  
Passwords  Avoiding password interception by using up to date  
anti-spyware and regularly changing passwords  
The differences between strong and weak  
passwords  
Other authentication methods  Including: zero login, biometric methods, magnetic  
stripes, smart cards, physical tokens, electronic  
tokens  
Anti-malware software  Including the use of anti-malware and anti-virus  
software  
The operation of removing/quarantining viruses  
using up to date software  
Scanning the storage media used to transfer data  
Scanning the data/software when downloading  
Electronic conferencing  Characteristics, uses, advantages and  
disadvantages of video-conferencing,  
audio-conferencing, web-conferencing  
The hardware, software and network connection  
required to set up each type of electronic  
conference  

Back to contents page 
5 




The effects of using IT 

5.1 Microprocessor-controlled devices 
Candidates should know and understand: 
The effects of using microprocessor-controlled devices 
Notes and Guidance 
The positive and negative effects of microprocessors/smart devices in monitoring and controlling devices in the home including the impact on lifestyle, leisure time, physical fitness, security of data, the degree of social interaction 
The positive and negative effects of microprocessors/smart devices in monitoring and controlling transport including security of data, autonomous vehicles, transport safety 

5.2 
Potential health problems related to the prolonged use of IT equipment 

6.3 
Computer controlled systems 



Candidates should know and understand:  Notes and Guidance  
Health  issues  Including: repetitive strain injury (RSI), back problems, eye problems, headaches  
The causes of these health issues and strategies for preventing them  

6  ICT applications  
6.1 Communication  
Candidates should know and understand:  Notes and Guidance  
Communication media  Characteristics and uses including newsletters,  
posters, websites, multimedia presentations, audio,  
video, media streaming and ePublications  
Mobile communication  The use of mobile devices for communication  
including: SMS messaging, phone calls, Voice over  
Internet Protocol (VoIP), video calls, accessing the  
internet  
6.2 Modelling applications  
Candidates should know and understand:  Notes and Guidance  
Computer modelling  Including: personal finance, bridge and building  
design, flood water management, traffic  
management, weather forecasting  
Advantages and disadvantages of using computer  
modelling rather than humans  

Back to contents page 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Computer controlled systems 
6.4 School management systems 
Candidates should know and understand: 
School management systems 
6.5 Booking systems 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Online booking systems 
6.6 Banking applications 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Banking applications 
6.7 Computers in medicine 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Information systems in medicine 
3D printers 
Notes and Guidance 
Including: robotics in manufacture, production line 
control, autonomous vehicles Advantages and disadvantages of using computer controlled systems rather than humans 
Notes and Guidance 
Systems are used to manage learner registration 
and attendance Systems are used to record learner performance including computer aided learning 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses, advantages and disadvantages of online booking systems including travel industry, concerts, cinemas, sporting events 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses, advantages and disadvantages of Automatic Teller Machines (ATM) including: withdrawing cash, depositing cash or cheques, checking account balance, mini statements, bill paying, money transfers 
Characteristics, uses, advantages and disadvantages of Electronic Funds Transfer (EFT), credit/debit card transactions, cheques, internet banking 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics and uses of patient records, pharmacy records 
Including printing of prosthetics, tissue engineering, artificial blood vessels, customised medicines 

Back to contents page 
6.8 Expert systems 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Expert systems 
6.9 Computers in the retail industry 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Computers in the retail industry 
Internet shopping 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses and purpose of expert systems including mineral prospecting, car engine fault diagnosis, medical diagnosis, chess games, financial planning, route scheduling for delivery vehicles, plant and animal identification 
Components of an expert system: user interface, inference engine, knowledge base, rules base, explanation system 
How an expert system is used to produce possible solutions for different scenarios 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics and uses of computers in the retail industry including point of sale (POS) terminals and electronic funds transfer at point of sale (EFTPOS) terminals 
Point of sale (POS) terminals including updating stock files automatically and ordering new stock automatically 
Electronic funds transfer at point of sale (EFTPOS) terminals including checking of the validity of cards, the use of chip and PIN, the use of contactless cards, the use of Near Field Communication (NFC) payment, the communication between the supermarket computer and the bank computer 
Characteristics, advantages and disadvantages of internet shopping 

Back to contents page 
6.10 Recognition systems 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Recognition systems 
6.11 Satellite systems 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Satellite systems 
7 The systems life cycle 
7.1 Analysis 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Analysis of the current system 
Record and analyse information about the current system 
System specification 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses, advantages and 
disadvantages of: Optical Mark Recognition (OMR) including school registers, multiple-choice examination papers, barcode, QR code 
Optical Character Recognition (OCR) including 
automated number plate recognition (ANPR) systems Radio Frequency Identification Device (RFID) including tracking stock, passports, automobiles, contactless payment 
Near Field Communication (NFC) including payment 
using a smartphone Biometric recognition including face, iris, retina, finger, thumb, hand, voice 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses, advantages and disadvantages of satellite systems including Global Positioning Systems (GPS), satellite navigation, Geographic Information Systems (GIS), media communication systems (satellite television, satellite phone) 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses, advantages and disadvantages of the research methods of observation, interviews, questionnaires and examination of existing documents 
The need to identify the inputs, outputs and processing of the current system, problems with the current system, the user and information requirements for the new system 
Identify and justify suitable hardware and software for the new system 

Back to contents page 
7.2 Design 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Design 
7.3 Development and testing 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Testing 
7.4 Implementation 
Candidates should know and understand: 
System implementation 
Notes and Guidance 
Design file/data structures, input formats, output 
formats and validation routines File/data structures including field length, field name, data type, coding of data for example M for male, F for female 
Validation routines including range check, character check, length check, type check, format check, presence check, check digit 
Input formats including data capture forms Output formats including screen layouts and report layouts 
Notes and Guidance 
The need to test the system before implementation Test designs, test strategies, test plan (test data, 
expected outcomes, actual outcomes, remedial action) following testing Test designs including the testing of data 
structures, file structures, input formats, output 
formats and validation routines Test strategies including to test each module, each function and the whole system 
The definition, characteristics and use of test data using normal, abnormal and extreme data The use of live data 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses, advantages and disadvantages of the four methods of implementation, direct changeover, parallel running, pilot running, phased implementation 

Back to contents page 
7.5 Documentation 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Documentation 
7.6 Evaluation 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Evaluate a solution 
8 Safety and security 
8.1 Physical safety 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Safety issues 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses and purpose of technical and 
user documentation Components of technical documentation including: purpose of the system/program, limitations of the system, program listing, program language, program flowcharts/algorithms, system flowcharts, hardware and software requirements, file structures, list of variables, input format, output format, sample runs/test runs, validation routines 
Components of user documentation including: purpose of the system, limitations of the system, hardware and software requirements, how to load/ run/install software, how to save a file, how to print data, how to add records, how to delete/edit records, input format, output format, sample runs, error messages, error handling, troubleshooting guide/helpline, frequently asked questions, glossary of terms 
Notes and Guidance 
Evaluate a solution including the efficiency of the solution, the ease of use of the solution, and the appropriateness of the solution 
Compare the solution with the original task requirements, identify any limitations and necessary improvements to the system, evaluate the users’ responses to the results of testing the system 
Notes and Guidance 
Including: electrocution from spilling drinks near electrical equipment and touching live cables, fire from sockets being overloaded or equipment overheating, tripping over trailing cables, heavy equipment falling and injuring people 
The causes of these safety issues and strategies for preventing them 

Back to contents page 
8.2 eSafety  
Candidates should know and understand:  Notes and Guidance  
Data protection  The principles of a typical data protection act and  
why data protection legislation is required  
Personal data  Characteristics of personal and sensitive data  
including personal name, address, date of birth, a  
photograph in school uniform, medical history  
The need for personal data to be kept confidential  
and protected to avoid inappropriate disclosure  
eSafety  The need for eSafety when using the internet,  
email, social media, online gaming  
Minimise the potential danger of using:  
The internet including only using trusted websites  
recommended by teachers, using a search engine  
that only allows access to age appropriate websites  
Email including an awareness of the potential  
dangers of opening or replying to an email from  
an unknown person. An awareness of the risks  
associated with sending personal identifiable data  
or images via email  
Social media including knowing how to block  
and report unwanted users, an awareness of the  
potential dangers of meeting an online contact face  
to face, avoiding the distribution of inappropriate  
images, avoiding the use of inappropriate language,  
respecting confidentiality of personal data of other  
people  
Online gaming including not using real names, not  
giving out personal or financial data  
8.3 Security of data  
Candidates should know and understand:  Notes and Guidance  
Threats to data  Characteristics and effect of threats to data  
including hacking, phishing, pharming, smishing,  
vishing, viruses, malware, card fraud  
Hacking including the measures that must be taken  
in order to protect data  
Phishing, pharming, smishing, vishing including the  
methods that can be used to help prevent them  
Viruses and malware including how to take  
preventative action to avoid the danger of infecting  
a computer from a downloaded file  
Card fraud including shoulder surfing, card cloning,  
key logging  

Back to contents page 
8.3 Security of data continued 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Protection of data 
9 Audience 
9.1 Audience appreciation 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Audience appreciation 
9.2 Copyright 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Copyright 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics and methods of protecting data including biometrics, digital certificate, secure socket layer (SSL), encryption, firewall, two-factor authentication, user id and password 
Biometrics including the use of biometric data Digital certificate including its purpose and contents Secure socket layer (SSL) including encrypted links 
between the server and the client computer Encryption including its purpose for the protection 
of data on hard discs, email, cloud, HTTPS websites Firewall including its purpose Two-factor authentication including its purpose and 
function User id and password including how they are used to increase the security of data 
Notes and Guidance 
Show a clear sense of audience and purpose 
Planning ICT solutions that are responsive to and respectful of the needs of an audience Analyse the needs of an audience when creating 
ICT solutions 
Notes and Guidance 
The need for copyright legislation and the principles of copyright relating to computer software (e.g. software piracy) 
The methods that software producers employ to prevent software copyright legislation being broken 

Back to contents page 
10 Communication 

10.1 Communication with other ICT users using email 
Candidates should know and understand: 
email 
10.2 Effective use of the internet 
Candidates should know and understand: 
The internet 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses and constraints of email communication including acceptable language, guidelines set by an employer, the need for security, netiquette, email groups, carbon copy (cc), blind carbon copy (bcc), forward, attachments 
Characteristics and effects of spam email including the methods which can be used to help prevent spam 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics, uses, advantages and disadvantages of using the internet including the differences between the internet, an intranet, an extranet and the World Wide Web (WWW), blog, forum, wiki, social networking 
Functionality including Internet Service Provider (ISP), structure of a web address, Uniform Resource Locator (URL), hyperlink, web browser 
Use of search engine including speed of searching, amount of information, the speed of finding relevant information, ease of finding reliable information 
Evaluating the information found on the internet including how up to date, reliable, biased and valid this information is 
Internet protocols including HyperText Transfer Protocol (HTTP), HyperText Transfer Protocol secure variant (HTTPS), File Transfer Protocol (FTP), Secure Socket Layer (SSL) 
Risks of using the internet including inappropriate and criminal material, restricting data through parental, educational and ISP control 

Back to contents page 
11 File management 
11.1 Manage files effectively 
Candidates should be able to: 
Manage files 
Candidates should know and understand: 
File formats 

11.2 Reduce file sizes for storage or transmission 
Candidates should be able to: 
Compress files 
Candidates should know and understand: 
File compression 
Notes and Guidance 
Locate stored files Open and import files of different types Save files in a planned hierarchical directory/folder 
structure Save files using appropriate file names Save and print files in a variety of formats including 
a document, screenshots, database reports, data tables, graphs/charts, a web page in browser view, a web page in HTML view 
Save and export in the file format of an application package including .docx, .doc, .xlsx, .xls, .sdb, .sdc, .accdb .odb, .rtf, .pptx, .ppt 
Save and export in a generic file format including .csv, .txt, .rtf, .pdf, .css, .htm, .jpg, .png 
Characteristics and uses of file formats including css, csv, gif, htm, jpg, pdf, png, rtf, txt, zip, rar The need for generic file formats 
Notes and Guidance 
Reduce file sizes for storage or transmission where necessary using file compression including .zip, .rar 
The need to reduce file sizes for storage or transmission 

Back to contents page 
12 Images  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Place and edit an image  Place an image with precision  
Resize an image as specified to maintain or adjust  
the aspect ratio of an image  
Crop an image  
Rotate an image  
Reflect (flip) an image horizontally or vertically  
Adjust the brightness of an image  
Adjust the contrast of an image  
Group and layer images including grouping and  
ungrouping, moving to the front or back  
Candidates should know and understand:  
File size reduction  Recognise that reducing the file size can be  
achieved by reducing the image resolution or colour  
depth  

13 Layout 

Note: In this section ‘document’ relates to any of the applications used within sections 16 to 21. 
13.1 Create or edit a document 

Candidates should be able to: Notes and Guidance 
Create a new document, or edit an existing Enter and modify text and numbers with total 
document accuracy 
Use editing techniques to manipulate text and 
numbers including highlight, delete, move, cut, 
copy, paste, drag and drop 
Place objects into the document from a variety of sources including text, image, screenshot, shapes, table, graph or chart, spreadsheet extract, database extract 
Wrap text around a table, chart or image including above, below, square and tight 

Back to contents page 
13.2 Tables 
Candidates should be able to: 
Work with tables within documents 
13.3 Headers and footers 
Candidates should be able to: 
Use headers and footers appropriately within a range of software packages 
Candidates should know and understand: 
The purpose of headers and footers 
14 Styles 
Candidates should be able to: 
Create, edit and apply styles 
Candidates should know and understand: 
Corporate house style 
Notes and Guidance 
Create a table with a specified number of rows and columns 
Place text or objects in a table Edit a table and its contents including insert row(s) and column(s), delete row(s) and column(s), merge cells 
Format a table including to set horizontal cell alignment (left, right, centre, fully justified), set vertical cell alignment (top, middle, bottom), show gridlines, hide gridlines, wrap text within a cell, shading/colouring cells, adjust row height, adjust column width 
Notes and Guidance 
Create or edit headers and footers Align the contents of the header and footer 
consistently within a document including to left margin, right margin and centred within margins Place text and automated objects in headers and 
footers including file information, page numbering, total number of pages, date, time 
Notes and Guidance 
Create, modify, update and apply styles to ensure 
consistency of presentation Font including font face, type (serif, sans-serif), point size, colour 
Text alignment including left, right, centre, fully justified 
Text enhancement including bold, underline, italic Spacing including paragraph (before and after) and line 
Bullets including shape, alignment, line spacing and indent 
Purpose and uses of a corporate house style 

Back to contents page 
15 Proofing  
15.1 Software tools  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Reduce errors  Use automated software tools (spell check,  
grammar check) and make appropriate changes to  
ensure all work produced contains as few errors as  
possible  
Use validation routines to minimise data entry errors  
Candidates should know and understand:  
Spell check software  Automated suggestions given by spell check  
software do not always give the correct response  
Validation checks  Importance, characteristics and uses of appropriate  
validation including range check, character check,  
length check, type check, format check, presence  
check  
15.2 Proofing techniques  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Perform visual verification  Identify and correct data entry errors including  
transposed numbers, incorrect spelling,  
inconsistent character spacing, inconsistent case  
Proofread  Identify and correct inconsistent line spacing,  
remove blank pages/slides, remove widows/  
orphans, inconsistent or incorrect application of  
styles, ensure that tables and lists are not split over  
columns or pages/slides  
Candidates should know and understand:  
Verification  Importance, characteristics and uses of verification  
including visual checking and double data entry to  
reduce data entry errors  
The need for validation as well as verification  

Back to contents page Back to contents page Back to contents page Back to contents page Back to contents page Back to contents page 
16 Graphs and charts  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Create, label and edit a graph or chart  Select data to produce a graph or chart including  
using contiguous data, non-contiguous data and  
specified data ranges  
Select the graph or chart type  
Label the graph or chart including chart title,  
legend, sector labels, sector values, percentages,  
category axis title, value axis title, category axis  
labels, value axis labels, data value labels  
Add a second data series  
Add a second axis  
Format numerical values to a specified number of  
decimal places  
Format numerical values to display currency  
symbols  
Adjust the maximum and minimum values of an  
axis scale and set incremental values  
Enhance the appearance of a graph or chart  
including extracting a pie chart sector, changing the  
colour scheme or fill patterns  
17 Document production  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Organise page layout  Edit page layout including page size, page  
orientation, page margins, number of columns,  
column width, spacing between columns, set and  
remove breaks (page, section and column breaks)  
Format text  Set line spacing including: single, 1.5 times, double,  
multiple, spacing before and after paragraphs  
Set tabulation including: left, right, centred and  
decimal tabs, indented paragraphs and hanging  
paragraphs  
Text enhancement including bold, underline, italic,  
superscript and subscript, changes in case  
Create or edit lists including bulleted, numbered  
Find and replace text  Including matching case, whole words  
Navigation  Add and delete bookmarks/hyperlinks  
Candidates should know and understand:  
Pagination  The purpose of setting page, section and column  
breaks  
Gutter margin  The purpose of setting gutter margins  

18 Databases  
18.1 Create a database structure  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Create an appropriate database structure  Import data from existing files (including .csv, .txt)  
using specified field names to create tables  
Set appropriate data types to fields including text,  
numeric (integer, decimal, currency), date/time,  
Boolean/logical  
Set sub-types of numeric data including  
percentage, number of decimal places  
Set display format of Boolean/logical field (yes/no,  
true/false, checkbox)  
Set display format of date/time data  
Create and edit primary and foreign keys  
Create relationships between tables  
Create and use a data entry form  Create a data entry form including specified fields,  
appropriate font styles and sizes, appropriate  
spacing between fields, character spacing of  
individual fields, use of white space, radio buttons,  
check boxes, drop down menus  
Candidates should know and understand:  
Types of database  Characteristics, uses, advantages and  
disadvantages of a flat file and a relational database  
Primary and foreign keys  Characteristics of primary key and foreign keys  
Form design  Characteristics of good form design  
18.2 Manipulate data  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Perform calculations  Use arithmetic operations or numeric functions to  
perform calculations including calculated fields,  
calculated controls  
Use formulae and functions to perform calculations  
at run time including addition, subtraction,  
multiplication, division, sum, average, maximum,  
minimum, count  
Sort data  Use a single criterion, or multiple criteria to sort  
data into ascending or descending order  
Search and select data  Use a single criterion, or multiple criteria to select  
subsets of data using a query  
perform searches using a variety of operators  
including AND, OR, NOT, LIKE, >, <, =, >=, <=, <>  
perform searches using wildcards  

18.3 Present data  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Display data  Produce reports to display data including displaying  
all the required data and labels in full  
Use appropriate headers and footers within a  
database report including report header, report  
footer, page header, page footer  
Set report titles  
Produce different output layouts including  
controlling the display of data, labels, tabular or  
columnar format  
Align data and labels appropriately including right  
aligning numeric data and decimal alignment  
Control the display format of numeric data including  
number of decimal places, currency symbol,  
percentage  
19 Presentations  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Create a presentation  Create a new presentation using a text file  
Use a master slide  Insert and edit objects consistently including  
images, text, shapes, logos, slide headers and  
footers, placeholder position, automated slide  
numbering  
Format master slide objects including headings,  
subheadings, bullets, background colour  
Edit a presentation  Apply slide layout  
Insert a new slide  
Move or delete a slide  
Insert and edit objects on a slide including text  
(headings, subheadings, bulleted lists), images  
(still images, video clips, animated images), charts,  
tables, audio clips (sound), symbols, lines, arrows,  
call out boxes and shapes  
Add presenter notes  
Insert and edit a hyperlink including linking text  
or objects to a slide within the presentation, an  
external file or an email address  
Insert an action button including modifying settings  
to navigate to a specified slide or file  
Add alternative text/screentip to an object  
Apply consistent transitions between slides  
Apply consistent animation effects on text, images  
and other objects  
Hide slides within a presentation  

19 Presentations continued  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Output the presentation  Display the presentation for a variety of purposes  
including looped on-screen carousel, presenter  
controlled  
Print the presentation in a variety of layouts  
including full page slides, presenter notes,  
handouts  
20 Spreadsheets  
20.1 Create a data model  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Create and edit a spreadsheet model  Insert cell(s), row(s) and column(s), delete cell(s),  
row(s) and column(s), merge cells  
Create formulae using cell references  
Replicate formulae using absolute and relative cell  
references where appropriate  
Use arithmetic operators in formulae including add,  
subtract, multiply, divide, indices  
Use named cells and named ranges  
Use functions including sum, average, maximum,  
minimum, integer, rounding, counting, LOOKUP,  
VLOOKUP, HLOOKUP, XLOOKUP, IF  
Use external data sources within functions  
Use nested functions  
Candidates should know and understand:  
Formulae and functions  The difference between a formula and a function  
Order of operations  The order in which mathematical operations are  
performed including the use brackets to make sure  
that formulae work  
Cell referencing  Characteristics and use of absolute and relative cell  
referencing  

20.2 Manipulate data  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Sort data  Using a single criterion, or multiple criteria sort data  
into ascending or descending order  
Search and select data  Using a single criterion, or multiple criteria, select  
subsets of data  
Perform searches using a variety of operators  
including AND, OR, NOT, >, <, =, >=, <=, <>  
Perform searches using wildcards  
20.3 Present data  
Candidates should be able to:  Notes and Guidance  
Adjust the display features  Display either formulae or values  
Adjust row height, column width and cell sizes so  
that all data, labels, and formulae is fully visible  
Wrap text within cells so that all data is fully visible  
Hide and display rows and columns  
Format a spreadsheet  Enhance a spreadsheet including text colour, cell  
colour, bold, underline, italic, shading  
Format numeric data appropriately including to  
display the number of decimal places, different  
currency symbols, percentages  
Use conditional formatting to change the display  
format depending on the contents of a cell  
Set page layout  Set the orientation to portrait or landscape  
Control the page layout to print including specified  
number of pages, print area, display or hide  
gridlines, display or hide row and column headings  
21 Website authoring  
21.1 Web development layers  
Candidates should know and understand:  Notes and Guidance  
The three web development layers  Content layer is used to enter the content and  
create the structure of a web page  
Presentation layer is used to display and format  
elements within a web page  
Behaviour layer is for a scripting language to control  
elements within a web page  

21.2 Create a web page 
Candidates should be able to: 
Use HTML in the content layer 
Notes and Guidance 
Create the content layer of a web page  Place appropriate elements in the head section of a web page including: 
• 
insert a page title to display in the browser 

• 
attach external stylesheets (with the correct hierarchy, using a relative file path) 

• 
metatags to use the appropriate attributes including to define the charset, name attributes (description, keywords, author, viewport), content attributes 

• 
default target windows 


Place appropriate content in the body section of a web page Insert a table including table header, table rows, 
table data Use appropriate table attributes to meet the needs of the audience including to adjust cells to span more than one row or column, to set table and cell 
sizes in terms of pixels or % values, to apply styles to tables Insert appropriate objects into a web page 
including text, images, sound clips, video (display controls, remove controls, autoplay), to adjust image or video size, aspect ratio and apply alternate text 
Use the <div> tag including to apply styles and 
classes Apply tags to text within a web page to display predefined styles including h1, h2, h3, p, li 
Apply classes to elements within a web page 
Apply styles to elements within a web page including to a list (ordered list, unordered list) Create a bookmark within a web page using an id 
attribute Create hyperlinks from text and images to: 
• 
bookmarks on the same page • other locally stored web pages 

• 
a website using the URL 

• 
send mail to a specified email address 

• 
to open in a specified location (the same window, a new window, with a window named as specified) 


continued 

Back to contents page 
21.2 Create a web page continued 
Candidates should know and understand: 
The use of HTML in the content layer 
21.3 Use stylesheets 
Candidates should be able to: 
Use CSS in the presentation layer 
Notes and Guidance 
Purpose of the head and body sections of a web 
page The reason tables are used to structure elements within a web page 
Function of metatags including to define: the charset, keywords for search engines, the author of the web page, a description of the web page, the viewport (to make your web page display on all devices) 
Function of a hyperlink 
Concept of a bookmark including methods of creating a bookmark within a web page Function of an anchor Relative file path and absolute file path including 
the reason absolute file paths must not be used for hyperlinks to locally saved web pages/objects 
Notes and Guidance 
Create the presentation layer of a web page Create generic external styles and inline style attributes including: 
• 
background properties including colour, images 

• 
font properties 

• 
table, table row, table header and table data properties including size, background colour, horizontal and vertical alignment, spacing, padding, borders: including collapsed, colour, thickness, visible/invisible 

Create classes including: 

• 
background properties including colour, images 

• 
font properties 

• 
table, table row and table data properties including size, background colour, horizontal and vertical alignment, spacing, padding, borders: including collapsed, colour, thickness, visible/invisible 


Create external styles to be tagged in a web page 
including h1, h2, h3, p, li Specify the font properties including font family, size, colour, alignment, bold, italic 
Attach comments to an external stylesheet Save styles in cascading stylesheet format 
continued 

Back to contents page 
21.3 Use stylesheets continued 
Candidates should know and understand: 
The use of CSS in the presentation layer 
Notes and Guidance 
Characteristics of cascading stylesheets including the difference between attached stylesheets and inline style attributes, the hierarchy of multiple attached stylesheets and inline styles within a web page 
Characteristics of a style and a class including the 
difference between them Reason relative file paths must be used for attached stylesheets 

Back to contents page 
4 Details of the assessment 
Paper 1 – Theory 
Written paper, 1 hour 30 minutes, 80 marks This is a compulsory paper consisting of multiple-choice, short-answer and structured questions. The questions are set on all sections of the subject content. Each individual question is set within separate contexts of ICT applications in everyday life. 
Candidates must answer all questions. Candidates answer on the question paper. 
Paper 2 – Document Production, Databases and Presentations 
Practical test, 2 hours 15 minutes, 70 marks For Paper 2 Document Production, Databases and Presentations, candidates must not have access to the internet or email. For each of the tasks, candidates will be provided with electronic source files; these files must be loaded onto the candidates’ computer system before the start of the examination. Please refer to the Cambridge Handbook for full details on the administration of this paper. 
This is a compulsory paper. It is a practical test which comprises a number of tasks to be taken under examination conditions and focuses on the candidate’s ability to carry out practical tasks by applying their knowledge and understanding to the following subject content sections: 
• 
Section 17 Document production 

• 
Section 18 Databases 

• 
Section 19 Presentations. 


Candidates demonstrate the practical skills relevant to sections 11–16. 
Candidates work through the steps of each task in order. Candidates are prompted to produce evidence of their work by creating screenshots and placing these within an Evidence Document and making printouts. It is essential that candidates remember to enter electronically their centre number, candidate number and name on each piece of evidence before it is sent to the printer. 
Back to contents page 
Paper 3 – Spreadsheets and Website Authoring 
Practical test, 2 hours 15 minutes, 70 marks For Paper 3 Spreadsheets and Website Authoring, candidates must not have access to the internet or email. For each of the tasks, candidates will be provided with electronic source files; these files must be loaded onto the candidates’ computer system before the start of the examination. Please refer to the Cambridge Handbook for full details on the administration of this paper. 
This is a compulsory paper. It is a practical test which comprises a number of tasks to be taken under examination conditions and focuses on the candidate’s ability to carry out practical tasks by applying their knowledge and understanding to the following subject content sections: 
• 
Section 20 Spreadsheets 

• 
Section 21 Website authoring. 


Candidates demonstrate the practical skills relevant to sections 11–16. 
Candidates work through the steps of each task in order. Candidates are prompted to produce evidence of their work by creating screenshots and placing these within an Evidence Document and making printouts. It is essential that candidates remember to enter electronically their centre number, candidate number and name on each piece of evidence before it is sent to the printer. 
Notes for guidance 
Hardware and software requirements 
Any hardware platform, operating system and applications packages can be used by candidates in the practical tests, provided that these packages have the facilities to enable the candidates to fully demonstrate all of the skills, performance criteria and assessment objectives in sections 11–21. 
It is recommended that for the website authoring section of the syllabus, candidates have a working knowledge of HTML and CSS. They may use suitable web editing software to assist them, but they will be required to edit the mark-up generated by such a package, or they may create their own HTML and CSS. 
There will be no requirement for candidates to use any scripting language. 
Back to contents page 
Command words 
Command words and their meanings help candidates know what is expected from them in the exams. The table below includes command words used in the assessment for this syllabus. The use of the command word will relate to the subject context. 
Command word What it means 

Analyse examine in detail to show meaning, identify elements and the relationship between them 
Compare identify/comment on similarities and/or differences 
Contrast identify/comment on differences 
Define give precise meaning 
Demonstrate show how or give an example 

Describe state the points of a topic / give characteristics and main features 
Discuss write about issue(s) or topic(s) in depth in a structured way 
Evaluate judge or calculate the quality, importance, amount, or value of something 
Explain set out purposes or reasons / make the relationships between things clear / say why and/or how and support with relevant evidence 
Give produce an answer from a given source or recall/memory 
Identify name/select/recognise 

Justify support a case with evidence/argument 
State express in clear terms 

Suggest apply knowledge and understanding to situations where there are a range of valid responses in order to make proposals / put forward considerations 
Back to contents page 
5 What else you need to know 
This section is an overview of other information you need to know about this syllabus. It will help to share the administrative information with your exams officer so they know when you will need their support. Find more information about our administrative processes at www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide 
Before you start 
Previous study 
We recommend that learners starting this course should have studied a broad curriculum such as the Cambridge Lower Secondary programme or equivalent national educational framework. 
We do not expect learners starting this course to have previously studied ICT. 
Guided learning hours 
We design Cambridge IGCSE syllabuses to require about 130 guided learning hours for each subject. This is for guidance only. The number of hours a learner needs to achieve the qualification may vary according to each school and the learners’ previous experience of the subject. 
Availability and timetables 
All Cambridge schools are allocated to one of six administrative zones. Each zone has a specific timetable. Find your administrative zone at www.cambridginternational.org/adminzone 
You can view the timetable for your administrative zone at www.cambridgeinternational.org/timetables 
You can enter candidates in the June and November exam series. If your school is in India, you can also enter your candidates in the March exam series. 
Check you are using the syllabus for the year the candidate is taking the exam. 
Private candidates can enter for this syllabus. For more information, please refer to the Cambridge Guide to Making Entries. 
Combining with other syllabuses 
Candidates can take this syllabus alongside other Cambridge International syllabuses in a single exam series. The only exceptions are: 
• 
Cambridge IGCSE (9–1) Information and Communication Technology (0983) 

• 
syllabuses with the same title at the same level. 


Cambridge IGCSE, Cambridge IGCSE (9–1) and Cambridge O Level syllabuses are at the same level. 
Group awards: Cambridge ICE 
Cambridge ICE (International Certificate of Education) is a group award for Cambridge IGCSE. It encourages schools to offer a broad and balanced curriculum by recognising the achievements of learners who pass exams in a range of different subjects. 
Learn more about Cambridge ICE at www.cambridgeinternational.org/cambridgeice 
Back to contents page 
Making entries 
Exams officers are responsible for submitting entries to Cambridge International. We encourage them to work closely with you to make sure they enter the right number of candidates for the right combination of syllabus components. Entry option codes and instructions for submitting entries are in the Cambridge Guide to Making Entries. Your exams officer has access to this guide. 
Exam administration 
To keep our exams secure, we produce question papers for different areas of the world, known as administrative zones. We allocate all Cambridge schools to an administrative zone determined by their location. Each zone has a specific timetable. 
Some of our syllabuses offer candidates different assessment options. An entry option code is used to identify the components the candidate will take relevant to the administrative zone and the available assessment options. 
Support for exams officers 
We know how important exams officers are to the successful running of exams. We provide them with the support they need to make entries on time. Your exams officer will find this support, and guidance for all other phases of the Cambridge Exams Cycle, at www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide 
Retakes Candidates can retake the whole qualification as many times as they want to. Information on retake entries is at 
www.cambridgeinternational.org/retakes 
Language This syllabus and the related assessment materials are available in English only. 
Accessibility and equality 
Syllabus and assessment design 
At Cambridge International, we work to avoid direct or indirect discrimination in our syllabuses and assessment materials. We aim to maximise inclusivity for candidates of all national, cultural or social backgrounds and candidates with protected characteristics, which include special educational needs and disability, religion and belief, and characteristics related to gender and identity. We also aim to make our materials as accessible as possible by using accessible language and applying accessible design principles. This gives all candidates the fairest possible opportunity to demonstrate their knowledge, skills and understanding and helps to minimise the requirement to make reasonable adjustments during the assessment process. 
Back to contents page 
Access arrangements 
Access arrangements (including modified papers) are the principal way in which Cambridge International complies with our duty, as guided by the UK Equality Act (2010), to make ‘reasonable adjustments’ for candidates with special educational needs (SEN), disability, illness or injury. Where a candidate would otherwise be at a substantial disadvantage in comparison to a candidate with no SEN, disability, illness or injury, we may be able to agree pre-examination access arrangements. These arrangements help a candidate by minimising accessibility barriers and maximising their opportunity to demonstrate their knowledge, skills and understanding in an assessment. 
Important: 
Requested access arrangements should be based on evidence of the candidate’s barrier to assessment and should also reflect their normal way of working at school. This is explained in the Cambridge Handbook 
www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide 
•  For Cambridge International to approve an access arrangement, we will need to agree that it constitutes  
a reasonable adjustment, involves reasonable cost and timeframe and does not affect the security and  
integrity of the assessment.  
•  Availability of access arrangements should be checked by centres at the start of the course. Details of our  
standard access arrangements and modified question papers are available in the Cambridge Handbook  
www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide  
•  Please contact us at the start of the course to find out if we are able to approve an arrangement that is not  
included in the list of standard access arrangements.  

• Candidates who cannot access parts of the assessment may be able to receive an award based on the parts they have completed. 
After the exam 
Grading and reporting Grades A*, A, B, C, D, E, F or G indicate the standard a candidate achieved at Cambridge IGCSE. 
A* is the highest and G is the lowest. ‘Ungraded’ means that the candidate’s performance did not meet the standard required for grade G. ‘Ungraded’ is reported on the statement of results but not on the certificate. 
In specific circumstances your candidates may see one of the following letters on their statement of results: 
• 
Q (PENDING) 

• 
X (NO RESULT). These letters do not appear on the certificate. 


On the statement of results and certificates, Cambridge IGCSE is shown as INTERNATIONAL GENERAL CERTIFICATE OF SECONDARY EDUCATION (IGCSE). 
Back to contents page 
How students and teachers can use the grades 
Assessment at Cambridge IGCSE has two purposes: 
1 to measure learning and achievement The assessment confirms achievement and performance in relation to the knowledge, understanding and skills specified in the syllabus. 2 to show likely future success 
The outcomes help predict which students are well prepared for a particular course or career and/or which students are more likely to be successful. The outcomes help students choose the most suitable course or career. 
Back to contents page 
Changes to this syllabus for 2026, 2027 and 2028 
The syllabus has been updated. This is version 2, published March 2025. 
There are no significant changes which affect teaching. 
You must read the whole syllabus before planning your teaching programme. We review our syllabuses regularly to make sure they continue to meet the needs of our schools. In updating this syllabus, we have made it easier for teachers and students to understand, keeping the familiar features that teachers and schools value. 
Changes to version 2 of this syllabus, published March 2025 
Changes to syllabus content We have added the percentage weighting of the Assessment objectives on page 10 


Any textbooks endorsed to support the syllabus for examination from 2023 are still suitable for use with this syllabus. 
Back to contents page 
School feedback: ‘While studying Cambridge IGCSE and Cambridge International A Levels, students broaden their horizons through a global perspective and develop a lasting passion for learning.’ Feedback from: Zhai Xiaoning, Deputy Principal, The High School Affiliated to Renmin University of China 
We are committed to making our documents accessible in accordance with the WCAG 2.1 Standard. We are always looking to improve the accessibility of our documents. If you find any problems or you think we are not meeting accessibility requirements, contact us at info@cambridgeinternational.org with the subject heading: Digital accessibility. If you need this document in a different format, contact us and supply your name, email address and requirements and we will respond within 15 working days. 
Cambridge Assessment International Education, The Triangle Building, Shaftesbury Road, Cambridge, CB2 8EA, United Kingdom t: +44 (0)1223 553554 email: info@cambridgeinternational.org www.cambridgeinternational.org 
© Cambridge University Press & Assessment September 2023 




