Cambridge Assessment International Education logo
Syllabus
Cambridge IGCSE™ (9–1)Arabic 7180
Use this syllabus for exams in 2026, 2027 and 2028.
Exams are available in the June and November series.
This syllabus is not available in all administrative zones. 
Please check the syllabus page at www.cambridgeinternational.org/7180 to see if this syllabus is available in your administrative zone.


Version 1
For the purposes of screen readers, any mention in this document of Cambridge IGCSE refers to Cambridge International General Certificate of Secondary Education.

Cambridge Pathway logo
Why choose Cambridge International?
Cambridge International prepares school students for life, helping them develop an informed curiosity and a lasting passion for learning. We are part of the University of Cambridge.
Our Cambridge Pathway gives students a clear path for educational success from age 5 to 19. Schools can shape the curriculum around how they want students to learn – with a wide range of subjects and flexible ways to offer them. It helps students discover new abilities and a wider world, and gives them the skills they need for life, so they can achieve at school, university and work.
Our programmes and qualifications set the global standard for international education. They are created by subject experts, are rooted in academic rigour and reflect the latest educational research. They provide a strong platform for learners to progress from one stage to the next, and are well supported by teaching and learning resources. Learn more about our research at www.cambridgeassessment.org.uk/our-research/
We believe education works best when curriculum, teaching, learning and assessment are closely aligned. Our programmes develop deep knowledge, conceptual understanding and higher-order thinking skills, to prepare students for their future. Together with schools, we develop Cambridge learners who are confident, responsible, reflective, innovative and engaged – equipped for success in the modern world.
Every year, nearly a million Cambridge students from 10 000 schools in 160 countries prepare for their future with the Cambridge Pathway. 
School feedback: ‘We think the Cambridge curriculum is superb preparation for university.’
Feedback from: Christoph Guttentag, Dean of Undergraduate Admissions, Duke University, USA


Quality management
Cambridge International is committed to providing exceptional quality. In line with this commitment, our quality management system for the provision of international education programmes and qualifications 
for students aged 5 to 19 is independently certified as meeting the internationally recognised standard, 
ISO 9001:2015. Learn more at www.cambridgeinternational.org/about-us/our-standards/



© Cambridge University Press & Assessment May 2024
Cambridge Assessment International Education is part of Cambridge University Press & Assessment. Cambridge University Press & Assessment is a department of the University of Cambridge.
Cambridge University Press & Assessment retains the copyright on all its publications. Registered centres are permitted to copy material from this booklet for their own internal use. However, we cannot give permission to centres to photocopy any material that is acknowledged to a third party even for internal use within a centre.

Contents
Why choose Cambridge International?.........................................................................2
1 Why choose this syllabus? .........................................................................................4
2 Syllabus overview ........................................................................................................7Aims	7
Content overview	8
Assessment overview	9
Assessment objectives	9


3 Subject content ..........................................................................................................11Writing 	11
Reading	11


4 Details of the assessment .........................................................................................12Paper 1 – Writing	12
Paper 2 – Reading and Grammar 	12


5 What else you need to know .....................................................................................13Before you start	13
Making entries	14
Accessibility and equality	14
After the exam	16
How students and teachers can use the grades	16
Changes to this syllabus for 2026, 2027 and 2028	17




Important: Changes to this syllabus
For information about changes to this syllabus for 2026, 2027 and 2028, go to page 17.


1 Why choose this syllabus? 
Key benefits	
Cambridge IGCSE is the world’s most popular international qualification for 14 to 16 year olds, although it can be taken by students of other ages. It is tried, tested and trusted. 
Students can choose from 70 subjects in any combination – it is taught by over 5000 schools in 150 countries.
Our programmes promote a thorough knowledge and understanding of a subject and help to develop the skills learners need for their next steps in education or employment. 
Cambridge IGCSE Arabic encourages learners to improve their use of Arabic in a range of contexts. Learners develop the ability to communicate effectively in writing, using a range of vocabulary and grammar, and to understand and respond to a variety of texts. These practical communication skills will equip them for higher education studies in Arabic-speaking environments.
Our approach in Cambridge IGCSE Arabic encourages learners to be:
confident, understanding language and communicating effectively, fostering resilience and adaptability in their language learning journey.
responsible, actively participating in their learning process and demonstrating how to use language for different purposes.
reflective, engaging in critical evaluation of their language skills and identifying areas for improvement.
innovative, applying their knowledge and understanding to explore creative ways to communicate and express themselves through language.
engaged, demonstrating curiosity in, and taking inspiration from, diverse perspectives and experiences.
School feedback: ‘The strength of Cambridge IGCSE qualifications is internationally recognised and has provided an international pathway for our students to continue their studies around the world.’
Feedback from: Gary Tan, Head of Schools and CEO, Raffles Group of Schools, Indonesia
International recognition and acceptance
Our expertise in curriculum, teaching and learning, and assessment is the basis for the recognition of our programmes and qualifications around the world. The combination of knowledge and skills in Cambridge IGCSE Arabic gives learners a solid foundation for further study. Candidates who achieve grades 9 to 4 are well prepared to follow a wide range of courses including Cambridge International AS & A Level Arabic.
Cambridge IGCSEs are accepted and valued by leading universities and employers around the world as evidence of academic achievement. Cambridge students can be confident that their qualifications will be understood and valued throughout their education and career, in their home country and internationally. Many universities require a combination of Cambridge International AS & A Levels and Cambridge IGCSEs or equivalent to meet their entry requirements.
UK ENIC, the national agency in the UK for the recognition and comparison of international qualifications and skills, has carried out an independent benchmarking study of Cambridge IGCSE and found it to be comparable to the standard of the GCSE in the UK. This means students can be confident that their Cambridge IGCSE qualifications are accepted as equivalent to UK GCSEs by leading universities worldwide.
Learn more at www.cambridgeinternational.org/recognition
School feedback: ‘Cambridge IGCSE is one of the most sought-after and recognised qualifications in the world. It is very popular in Egypt because it provides the perfect preparation for success at advanced level programmes.’
Feedback from: Managing Director of British School of Egypt BSE
Supporting teachers
We believe education is most effective when curriculum, teaching and learning, and assessment are closely aligned. We provide a wide range of resources, detailed guidance, innovative training and targeted professional development so that you can give your students the best possible preparation for Cambridge IGCSE. To find out which resources are available for each syllabus go to our School Support Hub. 
The School Support Hub is our secure online site for Cambridge teachers where you can find the resources you need to deliver our programmes. You can also keep up to date with your subject and the global Cambridge community through our online discussion forums.  
Find out more at www.cambridgeinternational.org/support
Support for Cambridge IGCSE
 
Planning and preparation
	•Syllabuses
	•Schemes of work
	•Specimen Question Papers and Mark Schemes
 Teaching and assessment
	•Endorsed resources
	•Online forums
 Learning and revision
	•Example candidate responses
	•Past papers and mark schemes
	•Specimen paper answers
 Results
	•Candidate Results Service
	•Principal examiner reports for teachers
 



Sign up for email notifications about changes to syllabuses, including new and revised products and services, at www.cambridgeinternational.org/syllabusupdates
Syllabuses and specimen materials represent the final authority on the content and structure of all of our assessments. 
Professional development
Find the next step on your professional development journey. 
	•Introductory Professional Development – An introduction to Cambridge programmes and qualifications.  
	•Extension Professional Development – Develop your understanding of Cambridge programmes and qualifications to build confidence in your delivery. 
	•Enrichment Professional Development – Transform your approach to teaching with our Enrichment workshops. 
	•Cambridge Professional Development Qualifications (PDQs) – Practice-based programmes that transform professional learning for practising teachers. Available at Certificate and Diploma level. 
Find out more at: www.cambridgeinternational.org/support-and-training-for-schools/professional-development/
Supporting exams officers
We provide comprehensive support and guidance for all Cambridge exams officers. 
Find out more at: www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide



2 Syllabus overview 
Aims
The aims describe the purposes of a course based on this syllabus. 
The aims are to: 
	•enable students to communicate accurately, appropriately and effectively in writing 
	•enable students to understand and respond appropriately to what they read 
	•encourage students to enjoy and appreciate a variety of language 
	•enable students to acquire a wide range of vocabulary and apply it alongside accurate grammar and spelling 
	•complement the students’ other areas of study by developing skills of a more general application (e.g. analysis, synthesis, drawing of inferences) 
	•promote the students’ personal development and an understanding of themselves and others.


Cambridge Assessment International Education is an education organisation and politically
neutral. The contents of this syllabus, examination papers and associated materials do not endorse 
any political view. We endeavour to treat all aspects of the exam process neutrally.



Content overview
Cambridge IGCSE (9-1) Arabic offers learners the opportunity to develop practical communication skills in reading and writing. 
Learners are encouraged to read a wide variety of texts and to engage with a diverse range of social and cultural topics throughout the course and use the knowledge gained to inform their own writing. They will be able to communicate facts and express their own viewpoints in writing and write effectively for different purposes and audiences. This will enable learners to become appreciative and independent users of Arabic. 
Assessment overview
All candidates take two components. Candidates will be eligible for grades 9 to 1.
All candidates take:
 and:
 
Paper 1	1 hour 30 minutes
Writing	50%
50 marks
Candidates answer two questions.
In Section A candidates answer one question from a choice of two questions. 
In Section B candidates answer one question from a choice of three questions.
Externally assessed
 Paper 2	1 hours 30 minutes
Reading	50%
50 marks
Candidates answer all questions.
Written exam consisting of exercises that test a range of reading comprehension, grammar and writing skills.
The task types are multiple-choice questions, short-answer questions and a summary.
Externally assessed
 



Information on availability is in the Before you start section. 
Assessment objectives
The assessment objectives (AOs) are:
AO1 Writing
Candidates should be able to:
	•W1. Present facts, and express ideas and opinions in order to interest, inform or convince.
	•W2. Communicate experience and express what is felt and what is imagined.
	•W3. Use appropriate register and style for the given audience.
	•W4. Organise ideas into coherent paragraphs using a range of appropriate linking devices.
	•W5. Manipulate the target language accurately to use appropriate examples of grammatical structures and vocabulary in context.
AO2 Reading
Candidates should be able to:
	•R1. Understand ideas, opinions and attitudes.
	•R2. Recognise explicit meaning, attitudes and ideas.
	•R3. Recognise implicit meaning, attitudes and ideas.
	•R4. Identify information and select what is relevant to specific purposes.
Weighting for assessment objectives
The approximate weightings allocated to each of the assessment objectives (AOs) are summarised below.
Assessment objectives as a percentage of the qualification
Assessment objective
 Weighting in IGCSE %
 
AO1 Writing
 55
 
AO2 Reading
 45
 
Total
 100
 



Assessment objectives as a percentage of each component
Assessment objective
 Weighting in components %
 
Paper 1
 Paper 2
 
AO1 Writing 
 100
 10
 
AO2 Reading
 0
 90
 
Total
 100
 100
 



3 Subject content 
This syllabus gives you the flexibility to design a course that will interest, challenge and engage your learners. Where appropriate you are responsible for selecting suitable subject contexts, resources and examples to support your learners’ study. These should be appropriate for the learners’ age, cultural background and learning context as well as complying with your school policies and local legal requirements.
The skills covered in the syllabus are outlined below:
Writing 
Candidates should be able to:
	•Organise and convey facts, ideas and opinions clearly and effectively in a particular form. 
	•Express what is thought, felt and imagined in order to interest, inform or convince the reader. 
	•Demonstrate an understanding of audience, purpose and form.
	•Use a range of grammatical sentence structures and use paragraphing appropriately.
	•Demonstrate a varied vocabulary appropriate to the context. 
	•Demonstrate accuracy in spelling, punctuation and grammar.
Reading
Candidates should be able to:
	•Demonstrate understanding of ideas, opinions and attitudes in written texts.
	•Demonstrate understanding of how writers achieve effects and influence readers.
	•Understand what is implied but not directly stated within a text, such as gist or inference.
	•Identify and select specific information within a text.
	•Summarise key points or information within a text and organise it in a logical manner.
	•Recognise and demonstrate understanding of linguistic devices and figurative language.
4 Details of the assessment 
Candidates take Paper 1 and Paper 2.
Paper 1 – Writing
Written paper, 1 hour 30 minutes, 50 marks, externally assessed.
Paper 1 assesses the Writing AOs. 
The paper contains two sections and candidates answer two questions in total. 
Candidates answer one question from a choice of two in Section A. Candidates can choose between a letter or a speech or report and are expected to write an extended answer of continuous prose. 
Candidates answer one question from a choice of three in Section B. Candidate can choose between a descriptive, a narrative or a discursive question and they will be required to write an extended answer of continuous prose.
Descriptive:
A descriptive piece of writing describes a person, place or situation, painting a picture with words so that the reader can picture it in his/her mind.
Narrative:
A narrative piece of writing tells a story containing a sequence of connected events which may be real or imaginary.
Discursive: 
A discursive piece of writing presents a balanced and objective examination of a subject. It does not, however, have to be expressly neutral. The response should present both sides of the discussion. 
Paper 2 – Reading and Grammar 
Written paper, 1 hour 30 minutes, 50 marks, externally assessed.
Paper 2 assesses the Writing and the Reading AOs.
The paper contain three sections and candidates should answer all questions.
In Section A, candidates read a short non-fiction text with gaps to be filled from multiple-choice options. The exercise tests understanding of grammatical usage in context.
In Section B, candidates read a short non-fiction text and answer a series of short-answer questions testing their understanding of the text. Candidates are then required to write a paragraph length summary (of around 100 words) about an aspect or aspects of the text.
In Section C, candidates read a short fiction text and answer questions that test their understanding of grammar or rhetoric and that require answers of a single word or phrase. Candidates are also required to transform four sentences, using the given prompts.
5 What else you need to know 
This section is an overview of other information you need to know about this syllabus. It will help to share the administrative information with your exams officer so they know when you will need their support. Find more information about our administrative processes at www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide
Before you start
Previous study
We recommend that learners starting this course should have studied a broad curriculum such as the Cambridge Lower Secondary programme or equivalent national educational framework.
Guided learning hours
We design Cambridge IGCSE syllabuses to require about 130 guided learning hours for each subject. This is for guidance only. The number of hours a learner needs to achieve the qualification may vary according to each school and the learners’ previous experience of the subject.
Availability and timetables 
All Cambridge schools are allocated to one of six administrative zones. Each zone has a specific timetable. 
Find your administrative zone at www.cambridginternational.org/adminzone. This syllabus is not available in all administrative zones. To find out about availability check the syllabus page at www.cambridgeinternational.org/7180
You can view the timetable for your administrative zone at www.cambridgeinternational.org/timetables
You can enter candidates in the June and November exam series. 
Check you are using the syllabus for the year the candidate is taking the exam. 
Private candidates can enter for this syllabus. For more information, please refer to the Cambridge Guide to Making Entries. 
Combining with other syllabuses
Candidates can take this syllabus alongside other Cambridge International syllabuses in a single exam series. The only exceptions are:
	•Cambridge IGCSE Arabic – First Language (0508)
	•Cambridge IGCSE (9–1) Arabic – First Language (7184)
	•Cambridge IGCSE Arabic as a Second Language (0544)
	•Cambridge O Level Arabic (3180)
	•syllabuses with the same title at the same level.
Cambridge IGCSE, Cambridge IGCSE (9–1) and Cambridge O Level syllabuses are at the same level.
Making entries
Exams officers are responsible for submitting entries to Cambridge International. We encourage them to work closely with you to make sure they enter the right number of candidates for the right combination of syllabus components. Entry option codes and instructions for submitting entries are in the Cambridge Guide to Making Entries. Your exams officer has access to this guide.
Exam administration
To keep our exams secure, we produce question papers for different areas of the world, known as administrative zones. We allocate all Cambridge schools to an administrative zone determined by their location. Each zone has a specific timetable. 
Some of our syllabuses offer candidates different assessment options. An entry option code is used to identify the components the candidate will take relevant to the administrative zone and the available assessment options.
Support for exams officers
We know how important exams officers are to the successful running of exams. We provide them with the support they need to make entries on time. Your exams officer will find this support, and guidance for all other phases of the Cambridge Exams Cycle, at www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide
Retakes
Candidates can retake the whole qualification as many times as they want to. Information on retake entries is at www.cambridgeinternational.org/retakes 
Language
This syllabus is available in English and Arabic. The assessment materials are in Arabic.
Accessibility and equality
Syllabus and assessment design 
At Cambridge International, we work to avoid direct or indirect discrimination in our syllabuses and assessment materials. We aim to maximise inclusivity for candidates of all national, cultural or social backgrounds and candidates with protected characteristics, which include special educational needs and disability, religion and belief, and characteristics related to gender and identity. We also aim to make our materials as accessible as possible by using accessible language and applying accessible design principles. This gives all candidates the fairest possible opportunity to demonstrate their knowledge, skills and understanding and helps to minimise the requirement to make reasonable adjustments during the assessment process. 
Access arrangements 
Access arrangements (including modified papers) are the principal way in which Cambridge International complies with our duty, as guided by the UK Equality Act (2010), to make ‘reasonable adjustments’ for candidates with special educational needs (SEN), disability, illness or injury. Where a candidate would otherwise be at a substantial disadvantage in comparison to a candidate with no SEN, disability, illness or injury, we may be able to agree pre-examination access arrangements. These arrangements help a candidate by minimising accessibility barriers and maximising their opportunity to demonstrate their knowledge, skills and understanding in an assessment. 
Important: 
Requested access arrangements should be based on evidence of the candidate’s barrier to assessment and should also reflect their normal way of working at school. This is explained in the Cambridge Handbook www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide 
	•For Cambridge International to approve an access arrangement, we will need to agree that it constitutes a reasonable adjustment, involves reasonable cost and timeframe and does not affect the security and integrity of the assessment. 
	•Availability of access arrangements should be checked by centres at the start of the course. Details of our standard access arrangements and modified question papers are available in the Cambridge Handbook www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide 
	•Please contact us at the start of the course to find out if we are able to approve an arrangement that is not included in the list of standard access arrangements. 
	•Candidates who cannot access parts of the assessment may be able to receive an award based on the parts they have completed.
Some access arrangements are not allowed in this syllabus because they affect the assessment objectives:
	•candidates must not use voice-activated software to dictate their written work
	•candidates must not use word processing technology which uses word prediction and/or phrase prompting including spell check and grammar check  
	•candidates must not use human readers.
Please note that we cannot provide Braille papers for this syllabus. We can only provide Braille papers for languages which use the Roman alphabet.
After the exam
Grading and reporting
Grades 9, 8, 7, 6, 5, 4, 3, 2 or 1 indicate the standard a candidate achieved at Cambridge IGCSE. 
9 is the highest and 1 is the lowest. ‘Ungraded’ means that the candidate’s performance did not meet the standard required for grade 1. ‘Ungraded’ is reported on the statement of results but not on the certificate. 
In specific circumstances your candidates may see one of the following letters on their statement of results:
	•Q (PENDING)
	•X (NO RESULT).
These letters do not appear on the certificate.
On the statement of results and certificates, Cambridge IGCSE is shown as INTERNATIONAL GENERAL CERTIFICATE OF SECONDARY EDUCATION (IGCSE).
How students and teachers can use the grades
Assessment at Cambridge IGCSE has two purposes:
1	to measure learning and achievement
	The assessment confirms achievement and performance in relation to the knowledge, understanding and skills specified in the syllabus.
2	to show likely future success
	The outcomes help predict which students are well prepared for a particular course or career and/or which students are more likely to be successful. 
	The outcomes help students choose the most suitable course or career.
Changes to this syllabus for 2026, 2027 and 2028
The syllabus has been reviewed and revised for first examination in 2026.
You must read the whole syllabus before planning your teaching programme.
Changes to availability
 This syllabus is now offered in the November series. 
 



In addition to reading the syllabus, you should refer to the updated specimen assessment materials. The specimen papers will help your students become familiar with exam requirements. The specimen mark schemes show how students should answer questions to meet the assessment objectives.
Any textbooks endorsed to support the syllabus for examination from 2026 are suitable for use with this syllabus.   




School feedback: ‘While studying Cambridge IGCSE and Cambridge International A Levels, students broaden their horizons through a global perspective and develop a lasting passion for learning.’
Feedback from: Zhai Xiaoning, Deputy Principal, The High School Affiliated to Renmin University of China

We are committed to making our documents accessible in accordance with the WCAG 2.1 Standard. We are always looking to improve the accessibility of our documents. If you find any problems or you think we are not meeting accessibility requirements, contact us at info@cambridgeinternational.org with the subject heading: Digital accessibility. If you need this document in a different format, contact 
us and supply your name, email address and requirements and we will respond within 15 working days.
Cambridge Assessment International Education, The Triangle Building, Shaftesbury Road, Cambridge, CB2 8EA, United Kingdom
t : +44 (0)1223 553554 	email : info@cambridgeinternational.org	www.cambridgeinternational.org
© Cambridge University Press & Assessment May 2024



