Cambridge Assessment International Education logo
Syllabus
Cambridge IGCSE™
Business Studies 0450
Use this syllabus for exams in 2026.
Exams are available in the June and November series.
Exams are also available in the March series in India.


Version 1
For the purposes of screen readers, any mention in this document of Cambridge IGCSE refers to Cambridge International General Certificate of Secondary Education.

Cambridge Pathway logo
Why choose Cambridge International?
Cambridge International prepares school students for life, helping them develop an informed curiosity and a lasting passion for learning. We are part of the University of Cambridge.
Our Cambridge Pathway gives students a clear path for educational success from age 5 to 19. Schools can shape the curriculum around how they want students to learn – with a wide range of subjects and flexible ways to offer them. It helps students discover new abilities and a wider world, and gives them the skills they need for life, so they can achieve at school, university and work.
Our programmes and qualifications set the global standard for international education. They are created by subject experts, are rooted in academic rigour and reflect the latest educational research. They provide a strong platform for learners to progress from one stage to the next, and are well supported by teaching and learning resources. Learn more about our research at www.cambridgeassessment.org.uk/our-research/
We believe education works best when curriculum, teaching, learning and assessment are closely aligned. Our programmes develop deep knowledge, conceptual understanding and higher-order thinking skills, to prepare students for their future. Together with schools, we develop Cambridge learners who are confident, responsible, reflective, innovative and engaged – equipped for success in the modern world.
Every year, nearly a million Cambridge students from 10 000 schools in 160 countries prepare for their future with the Cambridge Pathway. 
School feedback: ‘We think the Cambridge curriculum is superb preparation for university.’
Feedback from: Christoph Guttentag, Dean of Undergraduate Admissions, Duke University, USA


Quality management
Cambridge International is committed to providing exceptional quality. In line with this commitment, our quality management system for the provision of international education programmes and qualifications 
for students aged 5 to 19 is independently certified as meeting the internationally recognised standard, 
ISO 9001:2015. Learn more at www.cambridgeinternational.org/about-us/our-standards/



© Cambridge University Press & Assessment September 2023
Cambridge Assessment International Education is part of Cambridge University Press & Assessment. Cambridge University Press & Assessment is a department of the University of Cambridge.
Cambridge University Press & Assessment retains the copyright on all its publications. Registered centres are permitted to copy material from this booklet for their own internal use. However, we cannot give permission to centres to photocopy any material that is acknowledged to a third party even for internal use within a centre.

Contents
Why choose Cambridge International?.........................................................................2
1 Why choose this syllabus? .........................................................................................4
2 Syllabus overview ........................................................................................................7Aims	7
Content overview	8
Assessment overview	9
Assessment objectives	10


3 Subject content ..........................................................................................................12
4 Details of the assessment ........................................................................................25Paper 1 – Short Answer and Data Response	25
Paper 2 – Case Study	25
Command words	26


5 What else you need to know ....................................................................................27Before you start	27
Making entries	28
Accessibility and equality	28
After the exam	29
How students and teachers can use the grades	30
Changes to this syllabus for 2026	31




Important: Changes to this syllabus
The latest syllabus is version 1, published September 2023. There are no significant changes which affect teaching. 
Any textbooks endorsed to support the syllabus for examination from 2020 are still suitable for use with this syllabus.


1 Why choose this syllabus? 
Key benefits
Cambridge IGCSE is the world’s most popular international qualification for 14 to 16 year olds, although it can be taken by students of other ages. It is tried, tested and trusted. 
Students can choose from 70 subjects in any combination – it is taught by over 5000 schools in 150 countries.
Our programmes promote a thorough knowledge and understanding of a subject and help to develop the skills learners need for their next steps in education or employment. 
Cambridge IGCSE Business Studies is accepted by universities and employers as proof of an understanding of business concepts and techniques across a range of different types of businesses. Learners will be able to:
	•understand different forms of business organisations, the environments in which businesses operate and business functions such as marketing, operations and finance
	•appreciate the role of people in business success.
They will also gain lifelong skills, including:
	•the ability to calculate and interpret business data
	•communication skills needed to support arguments with reasons
	•the ability to analyse business situations and reach decisions or judgements.
Our programmes balance a thorough knowledge and understanding of a subject and help to develop the skills learners need for their next steps in education or employment. 
Our approach in Cambridge IGCSE Business Studies encourages learners to be:
School feedback: ‘The strength of Cambridge IGCSE qualifications is internationally recognised and has provided an international pathway for our students to continue their studies around the world.’
Feedback from: Gary Tan, Head of Schools and CEO, Raffles Group of Schools, Indonesia
International recognition and acceptance
Our expertise in curriculum, teaching and learning, and assessment is the basis for the recognition of our programmes and qualifications around the world. The combination of knowledge and skills in Cambridge IGCSE Business Studies gives learners a solid foundation for further study. Candidates who achieve grades A* to C are well prepared to follow a wide range of courses including Cambridge International AS & A Level Business.
Cambridge IGCSEs are accepted and valued by leading universities and employers around the world as evidence of academic achievement. Cambridge students can be confident that their qualifications will be understood and valued throughout their education and career, in their home country and internationally. Many universities require a combination of Cambridge International AS & A Levels and Cambridge IGCSEs or equivalent to meet their entry requirements.
UK ENIC, the national agency in the UK for the recognition and comparison of international qualifications and skills, has carried out an independent benchmarking study of Cambridge IGCSE and found it to be comparable to the standard of the GCSE in the UK. This means students can be confident that their Cambridge IGCSE qualifications are accepted as equivalent to UK GCSEs by leading universities worldwide.
Learn more at www.cambridgeinternational.org/recognition
School feedback: ‘Cambridge IGCSE is one of the most sought-after and recognised qualifications in the world. It is very popular in Egypt because it provides the perfect preparation for success at advanced level programmes.’
Feedback from: Managing Director of British School of Egypt BSE
Supporting teachers
We believe education is most effective when curriculum, teaching and learning, and assessment are closely aligned. We provide a wide range of resources, detailed guidance, innovative training and targeted professional development so that you can give your students the best possible preparation for Cambridge IGCSE. To find out which resources are available for each syllabus go to our School Support Hub. 
The School Support Hub is our secure online site for Cambridge teachers where you can find the resources you need to deliver our programmes. You can also keep up to date with your subject and the global Cambridge community through our online discussion forums.  
Find out more at www.cambridgeinternational.org/support
Support for Cambridge IGCSE 
 
Planning and preparation
	•Syllabuses
	•Schemes of work
	•Specimen Question Papers and Mark Schemes
	•Teacher guides
 Teaching and assessment
	•Endorsed resources
	•Online forums
	•Support for coursework and speaking components
	•Resource Plus
 Learning and revision
	•Example candidate responses
	•Past papers and mark schemes
	•Specimen paper answers
	•Test Maker
 Results
	•Candidate Results Service
	•Principal examiner reports for teachers
	•Results Analysis
 



Sign up for email notifications about changes to syllabuses, including new and revised products and services, at www.cambridgeinternational.org/syllabusupdates
Syllabuses and specimen materials represent the final authority on the content and structure of all of our assessments. 
Professional development
Find the next step on your professional development journey. 
	•Introductory Professional Development – An introduction to Cambridge programmes and qualifications.  
	•Extension Professional Development – Develop your understanding of Cambridge programmes and qualifications to build confidence in your delivery. 
	•Enrichment Professional Development – Transform your approach to teaching with our Enrichment workshops. 
	•Cambridge Professional Development Qualifications (PDQs) – Practice-based programmes that transform professional learning for practising teachers. Available at Certificate and Diploma level. 
Find out more at: www.cambridgeinternational.org/support-and-training-for-schools/professional-development/
Supporting exams officers
We provide comprehensive support and guidance for all Cambridge exams officers. 
Find out more at: www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide



2 Syllabus overview 
Aims
The aims describe the purposes of a course based on this syllabus. 
The aims are to enable students to:
	•apply their knowledge and critical understanding to current issues and problems in a wide range of business contexts
	•make effective use of relevant terminology, concepts and methods, and recognise the strengths and limitations of the ideas used in business
	•distinguish between facts and opinions, and evaluate qualitative and quantitative data in order to help build arguments and make informed judgements
	•appreciate the perspectives of a range of stakeholders in relation to the business environment, individuals, society, government and enterprise
	•develop knowledge and understanding of the major groups and organisations within and outside business, and consider ways in which they are able to influence objectives, decisions and activities
	•develop knowledge and understanding of how the main types of businesses are organised, financed and operated, and how their relations with other organisations, consumers, employees, owners and society are regulated
	•develop skills of numeracy, literacy, enquiry, selection and use of relevant sources of information, presentation and interpretation
	•develop an awareness of the nature and significance of innovation and change within the context of business activities
	•acquire a foundation for further study of business or other subjects.


Cambridge Assessment International Education is an education organisation and politically
neutral. The contents of this syllabus, examination papers and associated materials do not endorse 
any political view. We endeavour to treat all aspects of the exam process neutrally.



Content overview
1	Understanding business activity 
	This section introduces the underlying ideas and concepts of business and includes the purpose and nature of business activity and how businesses can be classified. Enterprise and entrepreneurs, and why some businesses grow while others remain small are further important issues. How business size can be measured, types of business organisation, business objectives and stakeholder objectives are the concluding topics.
2	People in business 
	The focus is the functional area of human resources and includes the importance and methods of motivating a workforce. How businesses are organised and managed and the methods of recruitment, selection and training of employees are also considered. Finally, the section covers the importance and methods of effective internal and external communication. 
3	Marketing 
	This section includes the role of marketing, the distinctions between niche and mass markets and the techniques of market segmentation. The methods and importance of market research are covered. The central role of the marketing mix, i.e. the four Ps, is made clear. Marketing strategies to influence consumer decisions at home and in new foreign markets are the final topics in this section. 
4	Operations management 
	The focus is the functional area of production and includes the meaning and methods of production and how productivity can be increased. The different costs of production and break-even analysis are covered. The section concludes with the importance and methods of achieving quality in the production process and location decisions of businesses. 
5	Financial information and decisions 
	This finance and accounting section covers the need for and sources of business finance, cash-flow forecasting and working capital. Simple income statements are covered as well as statements of financial position and the analysis of accounts including why and how accounts are used.
6	External influences on business activity 
	This section focuses on different external influences on business activity and how these impact on a business. It includes government influences on economic, environmental and ethical issues and how they impact on the functional areas of businesses. In addition, the international economy including globalisation and its effects on businesses and governments, multinational businesses and exchange rates are important issues. Legal constraints are an external influence to be considered but these influences are covered in the relevant functional areas above, as well as in this last section. 
Assessment overview
All candidates take two components. Candidates will be eligible for grades A* to G.
All candidates take:
 and:
 
Paper 1	1 hour 30 minutes
Short Answer and Data Response	50%
80 marks
Four questions requiring a mixture of short answers and structured data responses
Candidates answer all questions
Externally assessed
 Paper 2	1 hour 30 minutes
Case Study	50%
80 marks
Four questions based on a case study, provided as an insert with the paper
Candidates answer all questions
Externally assessed 
 



Information on availability is in the Before you start section. 
Assessment objectives
The assessment objectives (AOs) are:
AO1 Knowledge and understanding
	•demonstrate knowledge and understanding of facts, terms, concepts, conventions, theories and techniques commonly applied to or used as part of business behaviour.
AO2 Application
	•apply knowledge and understanding of facts, terms, concepts, conventions, theories and techniques.
AO3 Analysis
	•distinguish between evidence and opinion in a business context
	•order, analyse and interpret information in narrative, numerical and graphical forms, using appropriate techniques.
AO4 Evaluation
	•present reasoned explanations, develop arguments, understand implications and draw inferences
	•make judgements, recommendations and decisions.
Weighting for assessment objectives
The approximate weightings allocated to each of the assessment objectives (AOs) are summarised below.
Assessment objectives as a percentage of the qualification
Assessment objective
 Weighting in IGCSE %
 
AO1 Knowledge and understanding
 40
 
AO2 Application
 20
 
AO3 Analysis
 25
 
AO4 Evaluation
 15
 
Total
 100
 



Assessment objectives as a percentage of each component
Assessment objective
 Weighting in components %
 
Paper 1
 Paper 2
 
AO1 Knowledge and understanding
 50
 30
 
AO2 Application
 20
 20
 
AO3 Analysis
 20
 30
 
AO4 Evaluation
 10
 20
 
Total
 100
 100
 



3 Subject content 
This syllabus gives you the flexibility to design a course that will interest, challenge and engage your learners. Where appropriate you are responsible for selecting topics, subject contexts, resources and examples to support your learners’ study. These should be appropriate for the learners’ age, cultural background and learning context as well as complying with your school policies and local legal requirements.
In all of the following, candidates are required to apply their understanding to a variety of simple business situations. Candidates should be able to make simple decisions based upon the analysis and evaluation of information provided.
1	Understanding business activity
 
1.1	Business activity
 
1.1.1	&#7;The purpose and nature of business activity:
 	•Concepts of needs, wants, scarcity and opportunity cost
	•Importance of specialisation
	•Purpose of business activity
	•The concept of adding value and how added value can be increased
 

1.2	Classification of businesses
 
1.2.1	&#7;Economic sectors in terms of primary, secondary and tertiary sectors:
 	•Basis of business classification, using examples to illustrate the classification
	•Reasons for the changing importance of business classification, e.g. in developed and developing economies
 

1.2.2	&#7;Classify business enterprises between private sector and public sector in a mixed economy
 

1.3	Enterprise, business growth and size
 
1.3.1	&#7;Enterprise and entrepreneurship:
 	•Characteristics of successful entrepreneurs
	•Contents of a business plan and how business plans assist entrepreneurs
	•Why and how governments support business start-ups, e.g. grants, training schemes
 

1.3	Enterprise, business growth and size continued
 
1.3.2	&#7;The methods and problems of measuring business size:
 	•Methods of measuring business size, e.g. number of people employed, value of output, capital employed (profit is not a method of measuring business size)
	•Limitations of methods of measuring business size
 

1.3.3	&#7;Why some businesses grow and others remain small:
 	•Why the owners of a business may want to expand the business
	•Different ways in which businesses can grow, 
e.g. internal/external
	•Problems linked to business growth and how these might be overcome
	•Why some businesses remain small
 

1.3.4	&#7;Why some (new or established) businesses fail:
 	•Causes of business failure, e.g. lack of management skills, changes in the business environment, liquidity problems
	•Why new businesses are at a greater risk of failing
 

1.4	Types of business organisation
 
1.4.1	&#7;The main features of different forms of business organisation:
 	•Sole traders, partnerships, private and public limited companies, franchises and joint ventures
	•Differences between unincorporated businesses and limited companies
	•Concepts of risk, ownership and limited liability
	•Recommend and justify a suitable form of business organisation to owners/management in a given situation
	•Business organisations in the public sector, 
e.g. public corporations
 

1.5	Business objectives and stakeholder objectives
 
1.5.1	&#7;Businesses can have several objectives and the importance of them can change:
 	•Need for business objectives and the importance of them
	•Different business objectives, e.g. survival, growth, profit and market share
	•Objectives of social enterprises
 

1.5.2	&#7;The role of stakeholder groups involved in business activity:
 	•Main internal and external stakeholder groups
	•Objectives of different stakeholder groups
	•How these objectives might conflict with each other, use examples
 

1.5.3	&#7;Differences in the objectives of private sector and public sector enterprises
 

2	People in business
 
2.1	Motivating employees
 
2.1.1	&#7;The importance of a well-motivated workforce:
 	•Why people work and what motivation means
	•The benefits of a well-motivated workforce: labour productivity, reduced absenteeism and labour turnover
	•The concept of human needs, e.g. Maslow’s hierarchy
	•Key motivational theories: Taylor and Herzberg
 

2.1.2	&#7;Methods of motivation:
 	•Financial rewards, e.g. wage, salary, bonus, commission and profit sharing
	•Non-financial methods, e.g. job enrichment, job rotation, teamworking, training, opportunities for  promotion 
	•Recommend and justify appropriate method(s) of motivation in given circumstances
 

2.2	Organisation and management
 
2.2.1	&#7;Draw, interpret and understand simple organisational charts:
 	•Simple hierarchical structures: levels of hierarchy, span of control, chain of command e.g. tall/short
	•Roles and responsibilities of directors, managers, supervisors, other employees in an organisation and inter-relationships between them
 

2.2.2	&#7;The role of management:
 	•Functions of management, e.g. planning, organising, coordinating, commanding and controlling
	•Importance of delegation; trust versus control
 

2.2.3	&#7;Leadership styles:
 	•Features of the main leadership styles, 
e.g. autocratic, democratic and laissez-faire
	•Recommend and justify an appropriate leadership style in given circumstances
 

2.2.4	&#7;Trade unions:
 	•What a trade union is and the effects of employees being union members
 

2.3	Recruitment, selection and training of employees
 
2.3.1	&#7;Recruitment and selecting employees:
 	•Recruitment and selection methods 
	•Difference between internal recruitment and external recruitment
	•Main stages in recruitment and selection of employees 
	•Recommend and justify who to employ in given circumstances 
	•Benefits and limitations of part-time employees and full-time employees
 

2.3.2	&#7;The importance of training and the methods of training:
 	•Importance of training to a business and to employees
	•Benefits and limitations of induction training, 
on-the-job training and off-the-job training
 

2.3	Recruitment, selection and training of employees continued
 
2.3.3	&#7;Why reducing the size of the workforce might be necessary:
 	•Difference between dismissal and redundancy with examples 
	•Understand situations in which downsizing the workforce might be necessary, e.g. automation or reduced demand for products
	•Recommend and justify which employees to make redundant in given circumstances
 

2.3.4	&#7;Legal controls over employment issues and their impact on employers and employees:
 	•Legal controls over employment contracts, unfair dismissal, discrimination, health and safety, legal minimum wage
 

2.4	Internal and external communication
 
2.4.1	&#7;Why effective communication is important and the methods used to achieve it:
 	•Effective communication and its importance to business
	•Benefits and limitations of different communication methods including those based on information technology (IT)
	•Recommend and justify which communication method to use in given circumstances
 

2.4.2	&#7;Demonstrate an awareness of communication barriers:
 	•How communication barriers arise and problems of ineffective communication; how communication barriers can be reduced or removed
 
3	Marketing
 
3.1	Marketing, competition and the customer
 
3.1.1	&#7;The role of marketing:
 	•Identifying customer needs
	•Satisfying customer needs
	•Maintaining customer loyalty
	•Building customer relationships
 

3.1.2	&#7;Market changes:
 	•Why customer/consumer spending patterns may change
	•The importance of changing customer needs
	•Why some markets have become more competitive
	•How businesses can respond to changing spending patterns and increased competition
 

3.1	Marketing, competition and the customer continued
 
3.1.3	&#7;Concepts of niche marketing and mass marketing:
 	•Benefits and limitations of both approaches to marketing
 

3.1.4	&#7;How and why market segmentation is undertaken:
 	•How markets can be segmented, e.g. according to age, socio-economic grouping, location, gender
	•Potential benefits of segmentation to business
	•Recommend and justify an appropriate method of segmentation in given circumstances
 

3.2	Market research
 
3.2.1	&#7;The role of market research and methods used:
 	•Market-orientated businesses (uses of market research information to a business)
	•Primary research and secondary research (benefits and limitations of each)
	•Methods of primary research, e.g. postal questionnaire, online survey, interviews, focus groups
	•The need for sampling 
	•Methods of secondary research, e.g. online, accessing government sources, paying for  commercial market research reports
	•Factors influencing the accuracy of market research data
 

3.2.2	&#7;Presentation and use of market research results:
 	•Analyse market research data shown in the form of graphs, charts and diagrams; draw simple conclusions from such data
 

3.3	Marketing mix
 
3.3.1	&#7;Product:
 	•The limitations and benefits of developing new products
	•Brand image; impact on sales and customer loyalty
	•The role of packaging
	•The product life cycle: main stages and extension strategies; draw and interpret a product life cycle diagram
	•How stages of the product life cycle can influence marketing decisions, e.g. promotion and pricing decisions
 

3.3.2	&#7;Price:
 	•Pricing methods (benefits and limitations of different methods), e.g. cost plus, competitive, penetration, skimming, and promotional
	•Recommend and justify an appropriate pricing method in given circumstances
	•Understand the significance of price elasticity: difference between price elastic demand and price inelastic demand; importance of the concept in pricing decisions (knowledge of the formula and calculations of PED will not be assessed)
 

3.3.3	&#7;Place – distribution channels:
 	•Advantages and disadvantages of different channels, e.g. use of wholesalers, retailers or direct to consumers 
	•Recommend and justify an appropriate distribution channel in given circumstances
 

3.3.4	&#7;Promotion:
 	•The aims of promotion
	•Different forms of promotion and how they influence sales, e.g. advertising, sales promotion
	•The need for cost-effectiveness in spending the marketing budget on promotion
 

3.3.5	&#7;Technology and the marketing mix:
 	•Define and explain the concept of e-commerce
	•The opportunities and threats of e-commerce to business and consumers
	•Use of the internet and social media networks for promotion
 

3.4	Marketing strategy
 
3.4.1	&#7;Justify marketing strategies appropriate to a given situation:
 	•Importance of different elements of the marketing mix in influencing consumer decisions in given circumstances
	•Recommend and justify an appropriate marketing strategy in given circumstances
 

3.4.2	&#7;The nature and impact of legal controls related to marketing:
 	•Impact of legal controls on marketing strategy, e.g. misleading promotion, faulty and dangerous goods
 

3.4.3	&#7;The opportunities and problems of entering new foreign markets:
 	•Growth potential of new markets in other countries
	•Problems of entering foreign markets, 
e.g. cultural differences and lack of knowledge
	•Benefits and limitations of methods to overcome such problems, e.g. joint ventures, licensing
 

4	Operations management
 
4.1	Production of goods and services
 
4.1.1	&#7;The meaning of production:
 	•Managing resources effectively to produce goods and services
	•Difference between production and productivity
	•Benefits of increasing efficiency and how to increase it, e.g. increasing productivity by automation and technology, improved labour skills
	•Why businesses hold inventories 
	•The concept of lean production: how to achieve it, e.g. just-in-time inventory control and Kaizen; benefits of lean production
 

4.1.2	&#7;The main methods of production:
 	•Features, benefits and limitations of job, batch and flow production
	•Recommend and justify an appropriate production method for a given situation
 

4.1.3	&#7;How technology has changed and is changing production methods, e.g. using computers in design and manufacturing
 

4.2	Costs, scale of production and break-even analysis
 
4.2.1	&#7;Identify and classify costs:
 	•Classifying costs using examples, e.g. fixed, variable, average, total
	•Use cost data to help make simple cost-based decisions, e.g. to stop production or continue
 

4.2.2	&#7;Economies and diseconomies of scale:
 	•The concept of economies of scale with examples, e.g. purchasing, marketing, financial, managerial, technical 
	•The concept of diseconomies of scale with examples, e.g. poor communication, lack of commitment from employees, weak coordination
 

4.2.3	&#7;Break-even analysis:
 	•The concept of break-even
	•Construct, complete or amend a simple 
break-even chart
	•Interpret a given chart and use it to analyse a situation
	•Calculate break-even output from given data
	•Define, calculate and interpret the margin of safety
	•Use break-even analysis to help make simple decisions, e.g. impact of higher price
	•Understand the limitations of break-even analysis
 

4.3	Achieving quality production
 
4.3.1	&#7;Why quality is important and how quality production might be achieved:
 	•What quality means and why it is important for all businesses
	•The concept of quality control and how businesses implement quality control
	•The concept of quality assurance and how this can be implemented
 

4.4	Location decisions
 
4.4.1	&#7;The main factors influencing the location and relocation decisions of a business:
 	•Factors relevant to the location decision of manufacturing businesses and service businesses
	•Factors that a business could consider when deciding which country to locate operations in
	•The role of legal controls on location decisions
	•Recommend and justify an appropriate location for a business in given circumstances
 
5	Financial information and decisions
 
5.1	Business finance: needs and sources
 
5.1.1	&#7;The need for business finance:
 	•The main reasons why businesses need finance, e.g. start-up capital, capital for expansion and additional working capital
	•Understand the difference between short-term and long-term finance needs
 

5.1.2	&#7;The main sources of finance:
 	•Internal sources and external sources with examples
	•Short-term and long-term sources with examples, e.g. overdraft for short-term finance and debt or equity for long-term finance
	•Importance of alternative sources of capital, 
e.g. micro-finance, crowd-funding 
	•The main factors considered in making the financial choice, e.g. size and legal form of business, amount required, length of time, existing loans
	•Recommend and justify appropriate source(s) of finance in given circumstances
 

5.2	Cash-flow forecasting and working capital
 
5.2.1	&#7;The importance of cash and of cash-flow forecasting:
 	•Why cash is important to a business
	•What a cash-flow forecast is, how a simple one is constructed and the importance of it
	•Amend or complete a simple cash-flow forecast
	•How to interpret a simple cash-flow forecast
	•How a short-term cash-flow problem might be overcome, e.g. overdraft, delaying supplier payments, asking debtors to pay more quickly
 

5.2.2	&#7;Working capital:
 	•The concept and importance of working capital
 

5.3	Income statements
 
5.3.1	&#7;What profit is and why it is important:
 	•How a profit is made
	•Importance of profit to private sector businesses, e.g. reward for risk-taking/enterprise, source of finance
	•Difference between profit and cash
 

5.3	Income statements continued
 
5.3.2	&#7;Income statements:
 	•Main features of an income statement, 
e.g. revenue, cost of sales, gross profit, profit and retained profit
	•Use simple income statements in decision-making based on profit calculations (constructing income statements will not be assessed)
 

5.4	Statement of financial position
 
5.4.1	&#7;The main elements of a statement of financial position:
 	•The main classifications of assets and liabilities, using examples
 

5.4.2	&#7;Interpret a simple statement of financial position and make deductions from it, 
e.g. how a business is financing its activities and what assets it owns, sale of inventories to raise finance (constructing statements of financial position will not be assessed)
 

5.5	Analysis of accounts
 
5.5.1	&#7;Profitability:
 	•The concept and importance of profitability
 

5.5.2	&#7;Liquidity:
 	•The concept and importance of liquidity
 

5.5.3	&#7;How to interpret the financial performance of a business by calculating and analysing profitability ratios and liquidity ratios:
 	•Gross profit margin
	•Profit margin 
	•Return on Capital Employed
	•Current ratio
	•Acid test ratio
 

5.5.4	&#7;Why and how accounts are used:
 	•Needs of different users of accounts and ratio analysis
	•How users of accounts and ratio results might use information to help make decisions, e.g. whether to lend to or invest in the business
 

6	External influences on business activity
 
6.1	Economic issues
 
6.1.1	&#7;Business cycle:
 	•Main stages of the business cycle, e.g. growth, boom, recession, slump
	•Impact on businesses of changes in employment levels, inflation and Gross Domestic Product (GDP)
 

6.1.2	&#7;How government control over the economy affects business activity and how businesses may respond:
 	•Identify government economic objectives, 
e.g. increasing Gross Domestic Product (GDP)
	•Impact of changes in taxes and government spending 
	•Impact of changes in interest rates
	•How businesses might respond to these changes
 

6.2	Environmental and ethical issues
 
6.2.1	&#7;Environmental concerns and ethical issues as both opportunities and constraints for businesses:
 	•How business activity can impact on the environment, e.g. global warming
	•The concept of externalities: possible external costs and external benefits of business decisions
	•Sustainable development; how business activity can contribute to this
	•How and why business might respond to environmental pressures and opportunities, 
e.g. pressure groups
	•The role of legal controls over business activity affecting the environment, e.g. pollution controls
	•Ethical issues a business might face: conflicts between profits and ethics
	•How business might react and respond to ethical issues, e.g. child labour, paying fair prices to suppliers
 

6.3	Business and the international economy
 
6.3.1	&#7;The importance of globalisation:
 	•The concept of globalisation and the reasons for it
	•Opportunities and threats of globalisation for businesses
	•Why governments might introduce import tariffs and import quotas
 

6.3.2	&#7;Reasons for the importance and growth of multinational companies (MNCs):
 	•Benefits to a business of becoming a multinational and the impact on its stakeholders 
	•Potential benefits to a country and/or economy where a MNC is located, e.g. jobs, exports, increased choice, investment
	•Potential drawbacks to a country and/or economy where a MNC is located, e.g. reduced sales of local businesses, repatriation of profits
 

6.3.3	&#7;The impact of exchange rate changes:
 	•Depreciation and appreciation of an exchange rate
	•How exchange rate changes can affect businesses as importers and exporters of products, 
e.g. prices, competitiveness, profitability (exchange rate calculations will not be assessed)
 



4 Details of the assessment 
Paper 1 – Short Answer and Data Response
Written paper, 1 hour 30 minutes, 80 marks
The question paper comprises four questions requiring a mixture of short answers and structured data responses. 
The paper assesses content drawn from the entire syllabus. 
Each question is introduced by stimulus material. For some questions candidates will need to refer to the stimulus material in their answers. The stimulus material may include tables, graphs and images. 
Candidates answer all questions.
Candidates should be aware of the marks for each part question. These are printed on the question paper. Candidates should use them as a guide to the amount of detail and length of response expected and to help them manage their time effectively.
Candidates write their answers on the question paper. 
The paper assesses the following assessment objectives:
AO1: Knowledge and understanding
AO2: Application
AO3: Analysis
AO4: Evaluation
Paper 2 – Case Study
Written paper, 1 hour 30 minutes, 80 marks
The question paper comprises four questions based on a case study, provided as an insert with the paper. The case study includes appendices with data presented in a variety of forms, such as tables, graphs, newspaper extracts and advertisements. 
The paper assesses content drawn from the entire syllabus.
Candidates answer all questions.
Candidates should be aware of the marks for each part question. These are printed on the question paper. Candidates should use them as a guide to the amount of detail and length of response expected and to help them manage their time effectively.
Candidates write their answers on the question paper. 
The paper assesses the following assessment objectives:
AO1: Knowledge and understanding
AO2: Application
AO3: Analysis
AO4: Evaluation
Command words
Command words and their meanings help candidates know what is expected from them in the exams. The table below includes command words used in the assessment for this syllabus. The use of the command word will relate to the subject context.
Command word
 What it means
 
Calculate
 work out from given facts, figures or information
 
Consider
 review and respond to given information
 
Define
 give precise meaning
 
Explain
 set out purposes or reasons / make the relationships between things clear / say why and/or how and support with relevant evidence
 
Identify
 name/select/recognise
 
Justify
 support a case with evidence/argument
 
Outline
 set out the main points
 
State
 express in clear terms
 



5 What else you need to know 
This section is an overview of other information you need to know about this syllabus. It will help to share the administrative information with your exams officer so they know when you will need their support. Find more information about our administrative processes at www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide
Before you start
Previous study
We recommend that learners starting this course should have studied a broad curriculum such as the Cambridge Lower Secondary programme or equivalent national educational framework.
We do not expect learners starting this course to have previously studied Business Studies. 
Guided learning hours
We design Cambridge IGCSE syllabuses to require about 130 guided learning hours for each subject. This is for guidance only. The number of hours a learner needs to achieve the qualification may vary according to each school and the learners’ previous experience of the subject.
Availability and timetables 
All Cambridge schools are allocated to one of six administrative zones. Each zone has a specific timetable. 
Find your administrative zone at www.cambridginternational.org/adminzone 
You can view the timetable for your administrative zone at www.cambridgeinternational.org/timetables
You can enter candidates in the June and November exam series. If your school is in India, you can also enter your candidates in the March exam series.
Check you are using the syllabus for the year the candidate is taking the exam. 
Private candidates can enter for this syllabus. For more information, please refer to the Cambridge Guide to Making Entries. 
Combining with other syllabuses
Candidates can take this syllabus alongside other Cambridge International syllabuses in a single exam series. The only exceptions are:
	•Cambridge IGCSE (9–1) Business Studies (0986)
	•Cambridge O Level Business Studies (7115)
	•syllabuses with the same title at the same level.
Cambridge IGCSE, Cambridge IGCSE (9–1) and Cambridge O Level syllabuses are at the same level.
Group awards: Cambridge ICE 
Cambridge ICE (International Certificate of Education) is a group award for Cambridge IGCSE. It encourages schools to offer a broad and balanced curriculum by recognising the achievements of learners who pass exams in a range of different subjects. 
Learn more about Cambridge ICE at www.cambridgeinternational.org/cambridgeice
Making entries
Exams officers are responsible for submitting entries to Cambridge International. We encourage them to work closely with you to make sure they enter the right number of candidates for the right combination of syllabus components. Entry option codes and instructions for submitting entries are in the Cambridge Guide to Making Entries. Your exams officer has access to this guide.
Exam administration
To keep our exams secure, we produce question papers for different areas of the world, known as administrative zones. We allocate all Cambridge schools to an administrative zone determined by their location. Each zone has a specific timetable. 
Some of our syllabuses offer candidates different assessment options. An entry option code is used to identify the components the candidate will take relevant to the administrative zone and the available assessment options.
Support for exams officers
We know how important exams officers are to the successful running of exams. We provide them with the support they need to make entries on time. Your exams officer will find this support, and guidance for all other phases of the Cambridge Exams Cycle, at www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide
Retakes 
Candidates can retake the whole qualification as many times as they want to. Information on retake entries is at www.cambridgeinternational.org/retakes 
Language
This syllabus and the related assessment materials are available in English only. 
Accessibility and equality
Syllabus and assessment design 
At Cambridge International, we work to avoid direct or indirect discrimination in our syllabuses and assessment materials. We aim to maximise inclusivity for candidates of all national, cultural or social backgrounds and candidates with protected characteristics, which include special educational needs and disability, religion and belief, and characteristics related to gender and identity. We also aim to make our materials as accessible as possible by using accessible language and applying accessible design principles. This gives all candidates the fairest possible opportunity to demonstrate their knowledge, skills and understanding and helps to minimise the requirement to make reasonable adjustments during the assessment process. 
Access arrangements 
Access arrangements (including modified papers) are the principal way in which Cambridge International complies with our duty, as guided by the UK Equality Act (2010), to make ‘reasonable adjustments’ for candidates with special educational needs (SEN), disability, illness or injury. Where a candidate would otherwise be at a substantial disadvantage in comparison to a candidate with no SEN, disability, illness or injury, we may be able to agree pre-examination access arrangements. These arrangements help a candidate by minimising accessibility barriers and maximising their opportunity to demonstrate their knowledge, skills and understanding in an assessment. 
Important: 
Requested access arrangements should be based on evidence of the candidate’s barrier to assessment and should also reflect their normal way of working at school. This is explained in the Cambridge Handbook www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide 
	•For Cambridge International to approve an access arrangement, we will need to agree that it constitutes a reasonable adjustment, involves reasonable cost and timeframe and does not affect the security and integrity of the assessment. 
	•Availability of access arrangements should be checked by centres at the start of the course. Details of our standard access arrangements and modified question papers are available in the Cambridge Handbook www.cambridgeinternational.org/eoguide 
	•Please contact us at the start of the course to find out if we are able to approve an arrangement that is not included in the list of standard access arrangements. 
	•Candidates who cannot access parts of the assessment may be able to receive an award based on the parts they have completed.
After the exam
Grading and reporting
Grades A*, A, B, C, D, E, F or G indicate the standard a candidate achieved at Cambridge IGCSE. 
A* is the highest and G is the lowest. ‘Ungraded’ means that the candidate’s performance did not meet the standard required for grade G. ‘Ungraded’ is reported on the statement of results but not on the certificate. 
In specific circumstances your candidates may see one of the following letters on their statement of results:
	•Q (PENDING)
	•X (NO RESULT).
These letters do not appear on the certificate.
On the statement of results and certificates, Cambridge IGCSE is shown as INTERNATIONAL GENERAL CERTIFICATE OF SECONDARY EDUCATION (IGCSE).
How students and teachers can use the grades
Assessment at Cambridge IGCSE has two purposes:
1	to measure learning and achievement
	The assessment confirms achievement and performance in relation to the knowledge, understanding and skills specified in the syllabus.
2	to show likely future success
	The outcomes help predict which students are well prepared for a particular course or career and/or which students are more likely to be successful. 
	The outcomes help students choose the most suitable course or career.
Changes to this syllabus for 2026
The syllabus has been updated. This is version 1, published September 2023. 
You must read the whole syllabus before planning your teaching programme. We review our syllabuses regularly to make sure they continue to meet the needs of our schools. In updating this syllabus, we have made it easier for teachers and students to understand, keeping the familiar features that teachers and schools value.
There are no significant changes to syllabus content.
Any textbooks endorsed to support the syllabus for examination from 2020 are still suitable for use with this syllabus. 




School feedback: ‘While studying Cambridge IGCSE and Cambridge International A Levels, students broaden their horizons through a global perspective and develop a lasting passion for learning.’
Feedback from: Zhai Xiaoning, Deputy Principal, The High School Affiliated to Renmin University of China

We are committed to making our documents accessible in accordance with the WCAG 2.1 Standard. We are always looking to improve the accessibility of our documents. If you find any problems or you think we are not meeting accessibility requirements, contact us at info@cambridgeinternational.org with the subject heading: Digital accessibility. If you need this document in a different format, contact 
us and supply your name, email address and requirements and we will respond within 15 working days.
Cambridge Assessment International Education, The Triangle Building, Shaftesbury Road, Cambridge, CB2 8EA, United Kingdom
t : +44 (0)1223 553554 	email : info@cambridgeinternational.org	www.cambridgeinternational.org
© Cambridge University Press & Assessment September 2023



